Haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison
of a flat, secular materialism, to see and to know reality
as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen De Young,
host this live Colin show, focused on enchants.
In creation, the union of the scene and unseen as made by God and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
What is up, all of you giant killers, you dragon slayers, you stompers of scorpions and serpents.
You are listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host, Father Stephen D. Young is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana, thousands of miles away.
And I'm Father Interest even Damick in a-
Pennsylvania and we are live. So if you're listening to us live and not via
Memorax, you can call us at 855-237-2346 and you can talk to us. We're going to
get to your calls in the second half of the show and our own beloved
Montesca Trudy will be taking your calls. If you've ever had a chat with one of
our Calvinist friends about how he or she feels about other churches or
or theologies aside from Calvinism.
You may have
heard that person used the word idolatry. Not just Roman Catholics or us Orthodox either.
Idolatry is a big category for Calvinists that includes a lot. So what is idolatry?
And did the Orthodox with their love and veneration for iconography have an idolatry problem?
I mean, no. If you venerate just a little too much, did you do an idolatry? No.
So, all right, good night.
Yeah.
That just makes my necrotorical question pointless. Thank you very much for that one.
Oh, sorry, sorry, go ahead.
Come on, I'm monologue in here. You get to monologue for the rest of the show.
Anyway, yes. So tonight is the first to need two part series.
Tonight we're talking idolatry and next time we're talking iconography.
But here's the burning question that I know even Calvinists sometimes wonder about.
is American Idol.
real idolatry. Maybe. Is that the first maybe we've gotten? I think so. Because
Kelly Clarkson's career is kind of inexplicable otherwise. Huh. Huh. I mean that movie was terrible.
I did not see it so I was probably saved from... Anyway.
The Janet Colesaynals. Then somehow she gets a talk show like it's weird. It's weird. It's
It's weirder than Ricky.
like what's all I'm saying man I haven't thought about Ricky Lake in a lot of years
it would be kind of weird if you did I mean I think about the Roman Empire every day but if you
thought about Ricky Lake every day little odd I don't think I've even thought about her every year
yeah I don't remember every thought I had last year so who knows yeah I'm gonna go on
So we're yeah, we're doing we're doing this two parts
thing in part because lots of people we we've touched on this in various
episodes in various ways and but we haven't done an episode or episodes
really devoted to this and our approach here because I think this is part of
the problem is as you implied with your truncated setup.
rhetorical questions. Oh dear you sir. That people tend to see idolatry and
iconography somehow as if they're on a continuum. Yes. Right. And of course this
is because there are a lot of people from Protest especially evangelical
Protestant backgrounds who have been kind of taught that there is no
difference that religious iconography is idolatry.
Yes.
Or at least so easily becomes idolatry that it should be avoided.
Yeah.
You know, like these simple people, they're just doing what everybody else is doing
and they're probably slipping into idolatry.
Yes.
And so there's just this presupposition that there's it.
And I hear even very intelligent people I know from that background make these kind of
comments like, you know, St. Athanasia is here.
see he could dims idolatry and he doesn't mention Christian iconography so he
must have been an iconoclast. Yes, actual argument being made recently. Yes, my
intelligent person by the very excited. Yes, I'm very excited about his
argumentation. Yeah, not by a dumb person, but I did tell a
person. And that's sort of like saying, well, this church father condemned the
pagan Roman emperor and didn't mention bishops so he must
an anarchist, right? Like those don't follow, right? You know, a bishop and a pagan emperor who
declares himself to be a god, they're both authority figures. Okay. Right. They're religious.
Authority figures. Yes. They're religious. Because the emperor was the pontifax maximus of the Roman
cult, right? He was the high priest of the Roman cult, right? So
There are some superficial similarities, right?
But there are also much more major differences
in how these roles are completely conceived up.
And the same is true when you actually get into it
about idolatry and iconography.
Because there's also pagan iconography,
as we'll talk about next time.
Yeah.
Right.
paganism.
Idols and iconography were two different things.
Yeah. Yeah. I mean, idolatry and iconography basically share two things.
Images and religion.
Yes. That's not enough for either one to be what it is.
Like religious authority figures.
Like there's still a radical difference.
Right.
you know and and even though some of our Protestant friends would make the
arguments with idolatry and iconography, I dare say most of them unless they're like a quaker
wouldn't say, well hey look at the Pope, we can't have pastors. Right? So there are important
differences here. Right? And so what we're going to be doing is the next two episodes. Tonight,
we're doing idolatry in a couple of weeks we'll be doing iconography. Right? And we're going to
sort of ex-
explain what each of these things are, historically in their religious use.
Right. And so hopefully by us, back to back, sort of going through each of these phenomena,
people will be able to see, oh, no, these are two different things.
And so, you know, as you mentioned, your rhetorical question,
it's not like someone's going to walk into my parish.
and
Venerate the icon at the entrance too hard and accidentally do an idolatry
Like oh no
Wait back off. That's too many kisses pal. Throttle it throttle it. Right
Right, so these are these are two fundamentally
Different things right even though they both involve imagery
and both, and both of all of you.
And I will say here.
Because, you know, you mentioned it.
This sort of weird colonial idea that, you know,
the world is just full of these simpletons who don't have the kind of advanced religious sensibility I do.
Right? And, you know, so like if they watch a movie with someone playing Jesus in it,
they're just gonna stop.
worshipping the movie screen. Those ignorant peasants. Yes, right, then it was just a fool. Or if I've
seen it take a step, right, if you have a cross at the front of your church, they're just going to start
worshipping the wooden cross. Like they're just too dumb to make the distinction in their mind
between a wooden representation of the cross of Christ and God. Just too subtle for them.
them. And this is this is preposterous. And by the end of today, we're going to talk about just how
idolatrous many of our smartest and savviest folks are, right? Without their knowledge.
We're here to help. We're here to help. Or at least point a finger in condemn, you know, if not help.
I could just go full Pharisee if I need to.
So, yeah.
So we're going to start talking about idolatry where it arises, and of course idolatry arises,
all over the world simultaneously within paganism.
And this is another one of those things where someone recently online said, it comes
I'm going to take on one of our old episodes
where we had talked about how
just sort of everyone in the world
offered sacrifices and offered incense.
And therefore that's sort of the natural way
humanity worshiped.
They acted like that was ridiculous.
Yeah.
Because they're moving from a present-tist perspective, right?
Of like, you know, oh, why is that more natural
then with the
do in a Baptist church or what they do in a Buddhist
ashram or
I mean it's just a reality like this is what you see when you look at the
ancient world
yes and we try to have reality-based discussions here at Lord of
Spirits
rather than ideology-based discussions
so and this is just true
right and this is going back into the
Probably everyone has seen.
at some point, going back to the Neolithic era,
one of the earliest human crafted sculptures we have
is that Earth goddess.
Yeah, right.
Right, statue.
Idolatry just pops up everywhere, right?
In the archaeological records, everybody's doing it,
and this is why, as we'll get to, in the second half,
the Israelites have to be told in strictest terms,
Not to-
do it because everyone did it, right? It was what seemed natural to them. So as we've
talked about some of this right here at the beginning we're going to be reviewing, we're
going to be pulling together some things we've said in different episodes in the past.
So pagan worship as we've talked about in the past starts with certain essentially
natural places, meaning before people start building temples.
before people start constructing shrines,
they naturally occurring features
of the world become identified
and become the locations for sacrificial worship,
the offering of incense, right?
And other religious ritual.
And as we've talked about before,
these are generally places where
someone has had some kind of
of.
contact with a spirit. Yeah, so it's like groves,
enforests or, you know, clearings or on top of a cliff somewhere,
stuff like that. It's all right, you know, it's some geographic
feature that's recognizable in some way, typically. Right. And
delimitable, right? Like where you could say this is a place.
This is, yeah, this is the place. The other places around it are not
this place.
All right.
And so that as this begins to evolve, you start getting low fences, low rock walls, just
circles of stones, ways of delimiting that particular space, marking out that particular
space.
This is the space where the spirit that they hold to be divine was encountered, right?
That by at some point in the past.
And so this is the place where we returned to interact with, participate in that spiritual
Reallance.
And before you start getting what we would call idles proper, you start out with, again,
sort of unworked natural features.
So you get a tree, a large tree that's at the center of one of these spaces.
You get a pole, you get some kind of standing stone.
of these were deliberately...
the first shaping that happens to them is not carving them into human or animal forms,
but generally shaping them into fallacies if they didn't already look like that.
And this is what Ashropoles were that you read about the Old Testament.
They were large phallic symbols.
And the reason for that, of course, is that this is associated with fertility.
Yeah, and powered
virility, all that.
And we're not just,
I can stone,
both the fertility of the land and crops,
and the fertility of humans
and reproducing and having children,
which were the two key things to survival
as the neolithic revolution happens
and people start to do agriculture.
So these are the two people's two primary concerns.
So it's...
not a wonder that as they're interacting with the spirits that they believe are divine,
that it takes this form of seeking fertility.
And then from there, you start having those stones and those trees or poles or what have
you, being worked into more complex images and shapes.
the most part this starts out with animals, the figures of animals,
theriumorphic. That's the that's today's secret word is
theriumorphic. Well, not yet.
Oh,
dang it.
Actually, no, so in a minute.
Okay, okay, um, just getting excited. Yeah, about theriumorphism.
So now you start up.
with just animals. Right. So often as we've as we've talked about on the show before, this is bulls.
These are other animals that were taken to embody certain qualities. The bull, obviously, you can see how you can get there from the previous imagery, right of sort of virility power.
Yeah. Right. A bull being a male, right, sort of masculine power.
And then also
other animals, right, heifers, obviously related to that and other similar sort of imagery,
then we move into a stage where the spiritual beings were being interacted with or being
depicted and that's when you get the Theromorphic human animal forms.
The Egyptian gods mostly stuck with that.
Yeah, right.
as did the Hindu gods mostly stuck with that.
And you know, plenty of South American deities as well.
Yeah.
Yes, are sort of mixed human animal forms
or mixtures of different animals.
And then in some places like Greece,
at the end of the ancient Near Eastern period,
you start getting just humanoid.
pure humanoid depictions of deities, and those are generally shaped after a king or founder figure,
who they had previously, who while he was alive, or she, and was a sort of king or ruler,
or a founder figure, they believed embodied the divine while they were alive.
Right, so this king was thought to embody, right, the sky god, when they make statues of Zeus later, they make him look like that king.
Yeah, yeah. And this isn't just something we get from modern anthropology. There are future fathers who talk about this.
who say that the popular imagery of the Roman gods at their time, for example, is based on ancient kings.
Well, yeah, and I mean even get this later, like...
with Snorri Sturelson introducing the the the pros etta he basically says like that the Norse gods were just heroes from Troy that eventually came to be worshiped.
Right. Right. And it's probably more complex than that and that there's a give and take right of those gods already having been worshiped under some different form. Right. And then you get them. Algamy. Yeah.
Um.
in history, right? And so this is sort of what we see on the ground of the beginnings of idolatry,
is we said, this is pretty much universal, this is everywhere.
In the ancient Near East and other ancient cultures like the Indus River Valley,
this is all over the place, right? And it is still kind of true today, as we mentioned with India, right,
in terms of places, you know places where I Christian.
where chrysendum didn't exist, right? And you still find this sort of thing in many places. So,
that's what we find archaeologically and anthropologically. Of course, we talked about previously,
when we were talking about the story of the Tower of Babel, that part of the story of the Tower
of Bable is them trying to draw God down, right?
Them trying to...
use an idol to contain and interact with Yahweh, the God who created the universe, and
that of course goes badly for them.
Yeah, there's even fun traditions, I mean not mention in the Bible, but like from Second
Temple Jewish stuff that talk about Nimrod, you know, building the tower.
And number one, this is my favorite part.
If we build it high enough, then when God floods the place again, we'll escape this time.
And then also like the idea.
of, you know, and also while we're up there, we can make war on heaven and, you know, bring
him down. So it's just another way of that same, using a same kind of imagery of trying
to defeat God, you know? Yeah. Yeah. And so, um, that is sort of from the other side. Right.
I, I, I, Dollar Tree coming into, into being and they, uh, depiction of it. And so of course,
after that is God.
to protect humanity from his own holiness, so he won't destroy the world again as he did with the flood,
that angelic beings are assigned to the nations of the world, and it's from there that as we've talked about before,
that pagan worship and idolatry evolves as we see in the archaeological and anthropological record.
So how does
right? How did these idols function? How were they used? Whether we're talking about in a shrine
outdoors in the early phase or you know in the Roman Empire in Greece or Rome where you have a
temple with right V the statue of a god. Yeah, that means vast complex. centrally located. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah, like if you've ever if anybody's ever been to Lebanon and you've been to Baalbek
There's a temple to Zeus there which is just massive. I think it's the largest
excellent temple, you know, pagan temple in the world. I think it mostly got destroyed.
Oh, yeah, I mean, it's, it's not in good shape, but the site got destroyed recently.
Oh, really? Oh, like recently? Yeah. That's lame. I hope that's not true. I heard that
that happened in Palmyra and Syria.
I know that that was an issue, but I don't
have to hurt it.
ball block had an issue. But yeah, it's the name implies originally that was a shrine for bail.
But Zeus and bail kind of got assimilated starting with Alexander. Yeah.
So, um, yeah, so how are these idols functioning? How are they being used? Right.
So the idol first of all serves to localize.
the deity. Right, so a spirit right wasn't seen to have like doesn't obviously
doesn't have a material body. Right. In such a way that it's like, oh, well, yeah,
bail. He's the next town over. If you go over there, you can have a beer with him
the tavern, right? So you have to, you have to, he's a storm.
God too. So he's hanging out in the sky. You have to bring him down, right? You have to you have to have a place to meet with him. And so the the idol served to localize to bring the deity to that place.
And this becomes so true that there are particular
hypostasis and if me using that word freaks you out, listen.
disemold episodes. I'm not going to go through it again now. Of paying a
God's getting named after these places. Yeah, like Bale, Paylor, or
Artemis of the Ephesians. Right. Right. And this is why when you're reading
Homer, it seems like there's 87 different names for the same Greek God, right?
Because a lot of times he's using local names, right? Like localized place
to refer to.
to greet gods and goddesses,
and both the alien and the Odyssey.
So not only does this localize that deity to that place,
but it creates a version, right?
There's a body of that god now in that place.
That unless the temple and idol are destroyed,
Right, we'll remain there.
Yeah, and often they have like particular local characteristics too.
Like, you know, like it's not like statues of Stalin, which all kind of look the same.
I haven't studied statues of Stalin, but I'll take your word for it.
They have in Southern Lithuania, there is a museum of Southern of not Southern culture of Soviet culture.
And like they've they've collected a whole bunch of statues of Stalin and put them all and and and let him put them all there.
It's kind of funny to see him all as a group.
Yes, they do all kind of look the same, but these different idolatrous statues in different places will have different characteristics.
Right. Right. So I mean, Artemis and Ephesus is a good example.
If you look at the depictions of Artemis from Ephesus, from the Temple of Artemis there that was one of the Seven Wonders of the Ancient World,
And then you look at a depiction of Artemis from, say, the Peloponnese.
Right? They do-
don't look like the same woman. Right, right. Right. Right.
They're very different. And in Ephesus, this is very much a
fertility figure. Yeah. In the Peloponnes, this is very much
she's a huntress, right. These are sort of two different
sort of separate. So the localization is really right, the
humans creating a hypostasis of that God, essentially.
Right. And so then, the idle functions as the body of the deity in the way that we've
talked about bodies on the show, right, is this nexus of powers and potentialities, the
idea being this is the place where you can access that power, those abilities of this
spirit to bring fertility or victory in war or get someone to fall in love with you or
whatever it is.
looking for. But this is seen as the vehicle through which that can happen. And so because
this is the place of that access, this is also the place where you're going to come to try
to leverage that spirit to do what you want it to, meaning this is where you're going to
bring sacrifices. This is where you're going to bring food, right? This is where you're
going to bring gifts. This is where you're going to.
offer hospitality, right? You're going to go to the temple to do this, to continue this
ingratiating, right, relationship between your people and this spirit that you have chosen to associate with.
And you're also going to care for this deity, you're going to clothe it, right? You're going to clean it.
do all the things that you that that like
the servants of a human king. Right? So if you imagine a human king in the ancient Near East,
he has all these servants, they come and they bathe him, they bring him food, they dress him,
right? They do, he tells them, right? And they ingratiate themselves to him. And then at least
typothetically he provides them with station rank, wealth, power and authority.
Right? So it's the same...
kind of idea, but transferred to what they hold to be a divine spirit. And this is important,
what we just said there about how idolatry worked is important to really understand what's going on
with the traditional Israelite and Jewish critique of idolatry, which is essentially that
that those things we just listed are self-contradictory.
Right?
Yeah.
So, if bail has the power to send rains in its season and give you crops and make your
wife fertile so you have lots of children, if you can do all that, how come if you tip
him over he can't stand back up?
Why can't he dress himself?
Why can't he eat himself?
Yeah, I mean that's why so much of the stuff in the scripture about idolatry is just
like satirizing it, you know, like it's a big joke.
Right. Right. So the whole idea is that you're interacting
with something powerful, but very clearly humans are more powerful
than it can't even make its own idol.
You have to go and chop down some wood, right?
And go and make an idol and then you burn the rest for, you know,
heat. And, but that's your effort. Right.
it. So there are much simpler things that they can't do. This is the core of what you see
in the Old Testament when idols are being critiqued. Right? And, you know, this goes on
and on. Right? The people have to come there and tell the God what is going on because
it doesn't know. Right? They have to come and explain it. Well, okay. So here's where
at war with these people and we have right, like...
It's self-contradictory, it doesn't make sense.
But ultimately, what an idol is within paganism is a sort of handle or a grip.
Right?
So, the image encapsulates the concept of the spirit or deity in a way that limits it.
Yeah, so it becomes...
the God of this spot or this people or this idea, you know, it's not.
That's it, they, like, yeah, it's, it's, it's one of the really important things to realize about
paganism is that no pagan religion ever says that their God is all powerful. Like they don't
even make that claim. It's not like, well, this one's, you know, like there's clashing claims
with Yahweh. They're not. They're not even clashing claims.
Yeah.
It's definitely impossible, right?
Because first of all, you have as we've talked about before the succession myth, right?
Whoever's the most high God now wasn't always.
And hypothetically, one of his sons could overthrow him tomorrow.
Right?
And our neighbors' gods exist too.
So they might come over here and whip up on us, and that'll mean their gods are whipping
up on our gods.
Right?
And they could get killed.
can die, but yes, they're they're they become innately limited by having this this image, right?
Because the image, the idol, is essentially the visual equivalent of a definition.
Yeah. Right. So when you write the definition of a word or a concept, you are limiting it.
Yeah, it's this and not that.
Right. You're saying it is and it is just this. Right. Right. Just this is what we mean when we say it and
The idol does that visually
Right, the idol does that visually it says this divine spirit is this
It has these qualities as opposed to some other potential qualities
right
and
so but this is required
required, right, if human
are going to have any kind of control or leverage over such a spiritual entity.
Because if it's unlimited, right, then you're sunk.
We read the quote in an early episode when we were talking about primitive monotheism
from the anthropologist who talked about how, you know, petty gods became much more popular
the idea of a single
all powerful God who created and rules the universe because the single all powerful
God who created and rules the universe doesn't need anything from you.
Yeah, so there's no advantage to, you know, you can't get anything out of him.
Right. There's no way to get him to do what you want.
Yeah. There's no way to write this is not a god anyone would have invented.
Yeah. Little petty gods and spirits. Right. Well, those, you know,
They're like humans, right? They want things. They like things and hate things and you can do a deal. Yeah, we can do so. So this limiting that happened that is enacted by making an idol, right, is the precondition for now.
Now that this thing is limited, now I can gain leverage over it.
Now I can manipulate it because it's limited like I am as a human.
And in fact, as we just mentioned...
in that critique, that Jewish and Israelite critique, right? It's actually kind of more
limited than me as a human, right? It's kind of more limited than me. Now, we as Christians
would say that's a function of the fact that humans are made in the image of God, right?
And idols aren't actually made in the image of God. At best they're made in the image
of a human and your one step removed.
usually it's animals, it's things that are subhuman. And so this now means I can gain in some sense power
over the divine, over these spirits that are at work in the world around me. So there are lots of
things in the world that are beyond my human control. If we're talking about during the Neolithic
revolution the big two that we mentioned, right?
Is there are the rains gonna come?
Yeah, because water my crops.
They don't. That's the death of your people.
Yes. Yes. That's my kids all die.
My family all dies. Maybe my whole tribe in clan dies
because we don't have food.
Right.
And so are the rains gonna come?
Are the crops gonna grow?
Am I gonna have a good harvest?
Locusts gonna come through and eat it.
and write all these variables that I can't control.
You know, and are the are the women gonna have babies? Yes, that being the other one
I'm able to get my wife pregnant because they have zero scientific knowledge about how that even works
Yes, I can safely say for most of human history
Humans didn't understand
that
male infertility could
be a thing. Right. That's how little they understood it. Yeah. Yeah. They thought all men were
completely potent and fertile. And it was just a question of the woman. That's how little they
understood how human reproduction works. Um, so it's this mysterious thing. I can't control it.
Right. There there was and the infant mortality rate was super high. So, right. These are these out
of control things that my existence.
my family's existence, my communities' existence, my whole people's existence, depend on these.
Yeah, and you, so you're going to want divine power to try to give you a hand.
And they did not have the impression that these things were out of control.
They did not have the impression that everything was an accident and,
and you know, molecules bouncing off of each other, right?
This is under some things control. I need to get control of that something.
Yeah, right.
So this was the way to do it.
You take that thing, right?
You take fertility, this big thing that's out of your control
and you define it and you limit it, right?
And now you can exert leverage on it.
You've got to handle on it.
You can get a grip on it and you can try to take control
of your destiny, right?
And from a certain perspective, right?
We can see how this idea of trying to reduce the divine
into the human or the subhuman is sort of the reverse of the incarnation. Now, this
is the incarnation properly understood. And unfortunately, in a lot of Christian circles
today, the incarnation is not properly understood. So the way Christianity has seen the incarnation
Historically is not that Jesus was God and he somehow
committed himself and became just a human for a while.
That is not the doctrine of the incarnation
is taught by Christianity.
Doctor of the incarnation is taught by Christianity
is that Christ has elevated humanity
by taking upon himself our shared human nature.
So our human nature that he shares with us
has been elevated and united to God
in the person of Jesus Christ.
that
what the incarnation is about.
And so God becoming man is nothing like ancient idolatry,
or how they understood their God kings.
Right?
I mean, it really comes down from heaven and sumer.
It's a radical rebuke of all of that.
Right.
It's the opposite.
Yeah.
All right.
And that's why the second part of saying Athanasius is famous dictum.
Right? God became man so that man might become God is so important.
Yeah. Because if you lose that,
then you lose what's really going on.
So the incarnation is the exact opposite of this.
And this is part of why, especially, well, any feast of Christ that's concerned with the incarnation.
There's a few, the Annunciation,
because of his conception.
or obviously his nativity, you will see these references to Christ, to his
encouraging through his birth, has caused idolatry to cease. And that's because
of this understanding of what idolatry is. That the
It encourages fundamentally an inversion, a complete 180 of what idolatry was and how it worked.
So, someone might say, someone might bring up the Greek philosophers.
Right? And yes, to longtime listeners, I'm about to bash on Plato again.
But the way in which the Greek philosophers have been seen...
And Greek philosophy in general, and even Latin philosophy for that matter, have been
seen since, or really since the Renaissance, but especially since the Enlightenment, is
that they're seen as these people who sort of opted out of the religion of their time.
Yeah, there's this idea that, you know, everybody else is idolaters, but these guys are so smart
that they figured out.
These philosophical ideas that the religion of their day was dumb, turn their backs on all that idolatry stuff.
And this is not coincidental.
Right. This is the mark of the amateur historian.
Is that they look into the past and see themselves in a mirror.
Right.
And so if you think about the renaissance and then especially in the enlightenment
You have people who are renegades against the established religion of their own day.
Right? Who are rejecting Christianity as fables and all this, and favor of these philosophical ideas, and universal reason and all this, culminating in mass occurring a lot of people.
But it praises of universal reason and all this.
And so when they look back at Plato and Aristotle, Socrates at all.
They see, oh these were people like me, see, the pre-Christian era.
They were the smart ones.
They stood up to that goofy Greek religion that was going on at the time, right?
And in favor of universal reason.
This, of course, is poppycock.
Am I allowed to say poppycock?
There it is.
Let me check with the sensors.
I'll...
Okay.
Um, so
This is ridiculous, right?
And there are lots of things we could talk about here.
We could talk about the fact that Aristotle set up his school
inside a temple.
There's a bunch of good, but just to use Plato as an example,
right?
So Plato did see a problem.
If you read the youth of row, and the youth of row
is the platonic dialogue that's been the most warped
in terms of how modern people read it because of this.
What's really going on in the youth of Pro is that Plato kind of realizes that in the
mytho-ritual structures of his day and in the practice of idolatry, that this limiting
and sort of humanization, reducing to the human
of these divine spirits and powers and...
ideas has happened. But his answer to that is just to the problem is, oh, they've been
too humanized. Yeah. Yeah. And in fact, they've been so humanized that they could go and
do these horrible things. Right. And so Plato's forms are just the Greek gods with all the
human qualities.
So Plato's form of love and Aphrodite, the only difference is Plato's version of love is
not a woman does not have any kind of romantic or sexual relationships with other principles
right does not engage in petty jealousies does not cheat on a husband right those elements
throws out but
functionally, it's the same thing because he, through meditative practices, and even
through using the temples and the rituals of the day, saw people as coming to participate
in love.
Kinonia, it's the same word that's used for sacrificial ritual that he uses for the relationship
between the forms and humans.
So all he's doing is dehumanizing.
the gods and calling them the forms. Plato really was a pagan. Yeah, I mean he just had
what he saw as a more enlightened form of paganism. Yeah, and I mean some of the church
fathers of course saw good things in some of the stuff that he said and saw it as useful
for their purposes, but he still was an actual pagan.
Yes.
While he was alive on this earth at least for sure he was never a Christian. Yeah never Jewish
Yeah
and and
Sathies is a very pagan way and he saw the the idols and those stories and all of that as being
You know for the common folk
right because you got to remember also play
I don't believe
in aristocratic rationalism. He believed there were inferior and superior humans.
And he said, well, we philosophers are the highest tier of humans.
Right? Some people are born to be us and some people are born to be slaves.
And everything in between, right? And he said,
if those people beneath us, well, they can't understand these ideas. They can't understand what
justice is. Right so we you know we
We give them stories and we give them rituals and stuff to try to help them come to participate
in and understand justice, whereas we could just kind of look straight into the light,
right?
And have the sort of pure concept, right?
And by the way, this kind of view, right, like doesn't stop with Plato, right?
So you find this in a pair of ways.
Ibn Ra'oush, who's the great Muslim commentator on Aristotle, he literally says this about
Islam.
He says, Islam is philosophy for all the stupid pearls out there, right?
You don't, who can't understand philosophy, right?
So we give them Islam, right?
And there were a bunch of people in the West, when a Verwe's work, they're called the Latin
of Aeroists.
Thomas Aquinas was not one of them.
many ways he was reacting against them, but people like Cedra Debra...
want who took this approach to medieval period to Christianity. Christianity is for all
these peasants because they can't understand philosophy. Right? See also the afterward
to David Bentley Hart's book on universalism. But I'll leave that here. Right. But so Plato
sees part of this problem but he does
really overcome it. He's still within this pagan view. Right. He's just going to say, like he says
about everything else, that the actual idol of Athena sitting there in Athens is the shadow of an
image of wisdom of sort of pure divine wisdom. He doesn't say away with idolatry or stop. Stop.
No, in fact, in performing this necessary purpose.
all the dummies who can't understand wisdom per se. He just thinks he's in this better place,
right, where he can get to the core of it. He could sort of work back up the chain, right?
But even that view, even that view, if you pause and think about it a minute, remember what we
said about hypostasis of different gods and localizations. Plotters view is not that much different
than that. Right? This
statue is this shadow of an image, but that he can work back up the chain to get to the
spirit unlocalized.
Yeah, right.
It's really all he's saying.
He is still very much thinking and operating within that overall religious world view.
Um,
and I think a lot of this stuff gets misunderstood for that reason.
Aristotle basically just thinks that a lot of
Well
I'm not going to get into academic stuff I've been writing recently, but Aristotle basically
argues, for example, that tragedy is basically sacrificial ritual for an upper class of
people.
Right.
This is pretty well common in all their views, right?
But so moving on from that, what this means, we have to understand.
So whenever anybody thinks about anybody who is within or who has grown up within or is in a
society that holds to one religion, right, tends to view other religions in terms of that religion.
Yeah, right. Yeah. And so if you've grown up in a Christian culture and a Christian background,
Christian family of whatever type, right? You're gonna tend
to look at other religions from that perspective.
Right. Yeah. And I mean, I've, for instance, I've heard lots
of people say, oh, well, all religions are trying to get
salvation in their own way. And I'm like, actually, not all
religions are interested in anything called salvation. Yeah.
You know, it's just to start with. Yeah. And what that means can
be very different things. Yeah. Oh yeah. That could be anything
from eternal life to non-existence, depending on if you're
a Buddhist or a Christian, right? Yeah. Which are kind of
opposites, right?
So yeah, but you know, so it's very easy for us.
When we go back and look at Greek religion or Roman religion or Babylonian religion or
Canaanite religion or Egyptian religion, whatever one we want to choose, whatever slice
of paganism we want to take and be like, okay, well, what's their Bible?
Hesiod like their Bible.
is the pale cycle like they're viable as if they got together on one day a week and had
readings from it and somebody preached on it. Or to look at these in terms of beliefs.
Right, so it's like, oh, the Greeks believed there were like these 12 really powerful people
who lived on this mountain.
Right? Is if they had like tenets or a creed, right? And again, no, that's our thing, right?
They didn't have councils either. They didn't, right? That's so even what's meant by religion.
This is one of the classical problems, whether you're coming at religion from philosophy,
sociology, anthropology, right? One of the classical problems is how do you define religion?
Yeah, because the whole idea of A religion
And as we mentioned before on the show,
it's like a 16th, 17th century idea,
right, where it's like separated out
and you have different religions.
And this is a religion, right?
Modern concepts.
So trying to define it,
trying to come up with a definition of religion
that includes all religions,
everything you would think of as a religion,
it doesn't include a bunch of other things
that don't look like that people wouldn't think
are religions is almost impossible.
Oh
most impossible. But and that means that even what religion means is different. Right. So as
Christians, right, well, say, James says true religion, right? True piety is care for orphans and
widows. Yeah. That's not a definition shared by paganism. Right. Yeah. Definitely. So yeah.
The windows are at the bottom because they're it's God's of just
They were born to be that.
Yes.
But, right, so we might as Christians say, well, religion or piety is means that we participate
in certain religious rituals, particularly the Eucharist directed toward God whom we
We worship who created us that we observe certain standards.
of behavior in our lives, that when we violate those standards, we repent, and that we seek to do
works of charity in the world. Right, don't at me, I'm just doing this off of my head real quick,
right, someone might define Christianity that way. But none of that applies to paganism.
You can't just sub things out, you can't just say Zeus right in there and have it work, right?
So.
So pagan religion was primarily a form of tech-nay.
It was a craft.
It was a, they actually did engage in priest craft.
It was based on having certain knowledge and that knowledge was practical knowledge,
not esoteric knowledge about the origin or nature of the universe or the names of the
gods or something, but a very practical kind of knowledge.
So we mentioned before.
Or I know that in Exodus, the quote unquote magicians,
traditionally Janice and Jambres,
who confront Moses,
Pharaoh's quote unquote magicians
are actually what are called by historians now
lector priests, not related to Hannibal lector.
But lector is in reader, right?
And that's because the cast of priests at that time
Egypt their primary job was being able to
read. Hyratic has a lot of symbols. It's not an
alphabetical language. And so they were able to read the
already ancient documents, the ancient ritual text, to find
out the procedures needed, the procedures for burial, the
spells needed to enter into the afterlife, when something
would befall Egypt, Pharaoh would call them in and say, Hey,
there was a comment, Hey, there's a famine, Hey, what there's
Plagues from...
this Moses guy, what do we need to do to fix this? Right? What's the issue? What
gods do we need to appease? What do we need to do to make this situation right? And it
was then the job of those Egyptian priests to go consult those ancient texts and say,
okay, here's what we need to do. And tell them, you can think about other, right, the
the Haru specs, his whole job.
And even though that's the Latin term they used in Rome,
this is...
a priestly class all through the ancient Near East,
being able to read the entrails of sacrifices.
It was their job to learn how to do that.
These are the signs, right?
When we cut open the, when we're butchering the sacrifice,
when the primary ways they saw
whether the sacrifice was being accepted or not,
was to look for certain signs on different organs.
Oh, there's a black spot here.
Or it's a weird case that this organ is missing.
Or, right, these were all different omens and signs.
and those three.
needed to know how to identify those and then what needed to be done in response.
Rome famously had the sibling books which were hidden under one of the hills and under
a temple of Jupiter, cast of priests who was allowed to read the room of these books.
And so something went wrong in Rome.
They consulted the books which supposedly recorded the whole history and future of the world
said okay this is what we need to do to take
care that comment. This is what we need to do to take care of this ill omen, this failure
in war. Here's what we need to do. And that would include with those books like we need
to bury a couple of slaves alive in the marketplace. Okay, that's what we're doing. Um, but it was
this technique and having access based on practical knowledge, being able to read, being
able to consult, being able to interpret.
And so, idolatry is one of these techniques.
It's one of these ways of being able to access, interact with, control the spiritual realm,
the divine realm, right?
That's how it's seen.
Idolatry is a technique of particular access and manipulation of that realm.
And this is why you see in lists, like in the book of Inek, when you read the list of all
all the things that
the watchers, the demons before the flood taught to humanity.
One of them is idolatry.
Yeah.
And on a surface literal level, you might say,
well, what do you mean taught idolatry?
They taught him how to carve a statue to look like a person,
or to look like a dog person?
Like, what?
That's not what was being taught.
It's the whole technique, right, that we've
been talking about in outlining here,
of trying to control and manipulate the divine realm,
saying was taught by demons. So again, idolatry is not just making a piece of imagery.
Idolatry is everything else we've been talking about. The ritual elements, the control,
the manipulation, that's what idolatry is about. And so when you read in the Old Testament,
He revival other extra bibbuck
Jewish, anti- idolatry texts. They talk about those who worship them become like them.
Right? Again, as we've talked about before, this isn't saying that those gods don't exist.
Right? Because the people who worship them don't cease to exist. Right? But what happens is,
there's an inversion of control. They have attempted to, right? What they're trying to do
is take this
divine power, the spiritual power in the world, limited and gained control of it.
And instead of that happening, they become limited, they become controlled by the spiritual
power they were worshipping.
They are lowered and become something subhuman.
Right?
Dollar Tree Backfires is what that's saying.
What you're attempting to control, what you're attempting to do as a certain control over is going to end up controlling you.
That's what that becoming like them is about.
Yep.
Just backfires.
All right, well, that is the first half for this episode of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
We're going to take a little break and we will be right back with more.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take
your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
with Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237
two three four six that's eight five five a f radio
Welcome back everybody is second part of the show I like the water effects and that I know that was great right
We're getting did you hire a fully artist over there?
I should bet
Those are expensive did you know that like you can get those fully artists are still definitely a thing but oh, yeah
They are worth a lot of money.
Yeah, yeah, no, I'm just sitting here with a couple of buckets right here in the studio,
you know, playing that right behind Robbins voice over there.
So you're an amateur fully artist is what you're telling me.
That's right.
I need to get a raise.
I need to talk to a bit of somebody about that since I'm doing fully, fully, I don't know
where the fully comes from.
Yeah.
Anyway, you can all can give us a ring, 855 AF radio, just like the voice of Steve just
said.
Also, just want to give a little plug.
Father Steven is going to be speaking in Miami
at Christ the Savior, Orthodox Cathedral on October 7th.
And his topic is witchcraft and idolatry.
Hey, what do you know?
You can go to Orthodoxmiami.org for more info on that.
So all of you, South Floridians, this one's for you.
So how you figure out what you're going to talk about yet,
Father?
Of course not.
It's not going to next week.
you
whole plane flight. I got like, there you go. That's right. You can tap it out on the
the old tablet there. The thing is, even if I even if I did have a firm plan now of
what I was going to say next week, it wouldn't end up being what I say next week.
Change your mind. Yeah. I'm a maverick. Yeah. I'm a loner, daddy, a rebel. The first time
Paul Rubens. That's right. So the first time we've quoted him, no, because I
You know, this is tonight's secret word,
but this might be the first time
Pee was big adventure was quoted.
I don't know.
Not on the show at all,
because I know we've quoted things at the past.
Yeah, for sure.
And now you just put welcome back.
Hold room down.
You brought the whole room down.
Our stream died on Facebook though, by the way.
We're still on YouTube.
So of course, if you hear me,
then you don't know,
I can't tell you to go to YouTube,
but it's still on YouTube.
of course the engine.
Fade 3D app, still there, and the website, et cetera, et cetera.
And with the Facebook stream died, I'm sure there's like half a dozen confused
boomers trying to figure out how to listen to the show.
And they won't be able to, by the time it's over, they'll just have to listen to
the recording. So if you're listening to this recording tomorrow, sorry, I
called you a boomer.
It's okay to you six folks. I mean, if you're triggered by that, then what are
you doing listening to this podcast?
Yeah, exactly.
If you do expect me to be
Facebook again. Is this your first time? Welcome. So yeah so now here in the
second half we're going to talk about Israelite idolatry because it turns out
they did a lot of it. They did some idolatries. I don't know if you've read the
Old Testament but yeah, a whole bunch of idolatry.
Welcome home.
So, and we should say, so, again, I don't know why I watch these documentaries, I just do.
So setting aside for a second, the whole issue of whether monotheism is a very modern term,
one we need to worry about.
It has become stereotypical in any kind of archaeology-based
Old Testament Bible documentary,
or Hebrew Bible-based Bible documentary
to say two things.
First of all, the Old Testament says
that ancient Israel was monotheistic.
Number one, which as we've talked about before,
not true, but okay.
And then second that oh, but all of this archaeological evidence and all this other stuff
shows that they weren't
that they were actually polytheistic and worshipping all these pagan gods.
Now some of these people who say this
have PhDs in Old Testament or Hebrew Bible and or Hebrew Bible.
And this confuses me because it implies to me that they've never read it.
Because as we're about to go through, you can't swing a dead cat without hitting idolatry
in the Old Testament.
In fact, I will go so far as to say, your hard press to find any period in Israel's history
where according to the Bible, they were even monologous, let alone monotheistic.
Yeah.
that they weren't engaged in an idolatry according to the Bible.
So that's weird to me, but people say it,
and people who should know better say it,
and then folks who watch these documentaries
who maybe haven't read the Old Testament
or haven't read much of it, buy it.
Just believe what they're saying.
But let's, we're gonna go through and...
And Israel's idolatry can kind of be divided into two categories.
That's how we're going to approach it here.
First category is places where we're going to get, we're only giving examples.
Right? We like, we'd be here all night, like trying to go through every place.
The Bible talks about Israel being idolatrous, right?
But we're going to hit low lights.
So the first category is where they're used
idolatry directed toward Yahweh, the God of Israel. And then the second
category is when the scriptures talk about Israel engaging in idolatrous
worship of other gods alongside Yahweh, the God of Israel. So those are sort
of the two broad categories.
Both of the
these are bad. Right? And these are related to the first two
commandments. Right? So the second commandment is about not
making graven images and bound down to them. And certain
them, this is talking about idolatry. periods, this is saying
right, like don't try to worship Yahweh or God via idolatry.
Why? Because what are you doing? You're trying to do what they
did it at the top.
of Bable. You're trying to limit the God who created the universe. You're trying to limit the God
of Israel, trying to draw him down, limit it, get control of him and get him to do what you want.
So second commandment says you don't do that. First commandment is you'll have no other gods in my
presence. So that's our other category, right? You're not to worship these other gods alongside.
Right. Yep. And that again,
It's for largely the same reason because if you think about it, right, if you claim your worshiping
The only thing out of Israel the God who created everything
Right the most I got to create the universe who created everything else that gets called called gods whether we're talking about
about demonic spirits or dead human beings or live human beings.
human beings, right? God, the true God created all of those, right? If you claim
you're worshiping him, and then you say, Oh, but I need, I need to also sacrifice to bail
to make sure my crops are good. Yeah. Yeah. Can I, can I have this too?
Actually related to that, we do have a call. This person is, we have Simon calling from Detroit
Michigan apparently Simon is asking about what's the difference between worship and
because in Revelation 22, the angel says not to worship him.
So, I don't know.
That seems to be the summary of your question.
Simon, are you there?
Yeah, I'm here.
Good evening, Father.
Good evening.
So, I don't know.
Go ahead and ask your question.
Make sure that we understand what you're trying to get across.
Yeah.
I wish Father Andrew hadn't read that summary,
or at least not before I had said,
what does Simon say?
How often do you get that poor man?
I've never heard of it before ever.
Oh good, that's great.
It's original.
I like to break new ground.
Ever.
So my question is kind of a two-part question really.
I've always been a little bit confused
about worship and veneration especially after you guys
talked about I'm coming from a Protestant background.
I was preservationed last month, actually.
Oh, hey, congratulations.
Thank you.
And that was one verse I...
I was thinking about where John gets this vision, things like that from the angel, and he
bowed down to worship him, sounds like he's doing a prostration or something like that.
That uses the word worship at least twice in that passage, and then the angel tells him not
to worship him because he's just a servant of God like St. John is. And so I'm thinking,
making up our streets and do something.
is worship, is that what we're doing when we cross
straight for like the holy cross and things like that,
or is that just veneration?
That's not make sense.
Yes.
See, I can do monosolabic responses sometimes.
Are you?
Stealing my bit.
Well, it's a bit.
It works.
Right.
I mean, if I recall, I think we've talked about this before.
but if I recall correctly,
The point that the angel is making there is to say to say, John, I'm not the angel of the Lord,
so you should not be treating me as though I'm God himself. It's not that bowing or prostrating
is in and of itself bad because we see that happening between righteous people, for instance,
that bow down to the ground to each other and the other one doesn't say, whoa, whoa, stop it,
a idolatry.
You know, so I mean
And as we said, idolatry involves setting up an image, feeding and clothing it, understanding
it as controlling elemental forces and spirits.
That's a whole big ball of action and understanding that is not simply bowing or prostrating.
I don't know.
Father's anything you wanted to add or correct or subtract?
Well, I think the key thing that's going on there in context in Revelation is that that
An angel is...
differentiating himself from the figure of the glorified Christ who had been talking to St. John before that
Okay, right who didn't say the same thing
Yeah, right
So I think that's the main intent of that is like wait wait wait that's not me right that's I'm
I'm this other kind of thing
um
but also in general.
Because this covers a lot of questions we get, right?
Most people do not use most words as technical terms most of the time, right?
So when we talk about the distinction between worship and veneration, we're using those
as technical terms.
We're saying, worship is a, veneration is b, right?
But that doesn't mean that any time you see a hymn from 15 centuries ago that uses the word worship
or a writing of a church father from 800 years ago that uses the word veneration.
that every single time anyone in the Orthodox tradition or in the scripture
uses one of those two words, it means like the technical definition.
Yeah, like even in English, the word, we get the word,
the word worship in English, for most of its history,
has meant veneration.
You know, it hasn't meant sacrificing to a God.
Now, I mean, now we do use it in that way.
But mostly because it's connected to the word worth.
So it's just showing the worthiness of the other.
other. So if you said
you know, good day, sir, which is language of respect, right?
And honor, that is literally worshiping that other person,
according to that older sense of the word worship.
And it's why like British judges are called your worship.
No one thinks that they're being sacrificed to his gods.
It's just a form of respect.
So, so yeah, I mean, as Father said,
the words are not always used in these tight technical ways.
So the key...
This is the important thing. What is the action being done and what is the context of that action?
And is it part of a larger set of actions?
Right? Like you can put food in front of somebody. Let's say you wait table at a restaurant.
You can put food in front of someone and say there you go, sir.
So you've not only put food in front of a being, which is a spiritual being, because it's human,
but also said words of respect.
Does that make?
unidolator. Obviously not even though putting food in front of an image of a spiritual being
and saying words of respect is part of idolatry, there's a lot more going on in idolatry. Does that
make sense? Yeah, so just to clarify that frustration or whatever was happening there was
St John, buying down to the angel. That's not necessarily
worship. I mean, he didn't know.
sacrifice or anything to the angel. He just basically
venerated when it seems like is that correct?
Right. Yeah. I mean, the angel was making sure he knew that he
was just an angel and not Christ, who had previously been
talking to Saint John and it appeared to you. Yeah. Because
you know, when you're having a visionary experience, it can
be hard to figure out what's going on. Okay. Yeah.
All right. Well, thank you very much for calling Simon.
Thank you, Father.
You're welcome.
If you get into the original languages, it becomes even more complicated,
because the word in Greek that's usually translated as veneration,
and the word autoremos in Latin that's usually translated adoration or worship,
both literally mean to bend the knee.
Yep.
So, right. So that's what I mean by technical terms. Right. So, Latin speaking people
did not think that every time you bent your knee and bowed to someone you were worshiping
them, in some idolatrous sense. Right. And Greek speakers didn't think that if you
were bowing before an idol, that was okay because you were just venerating it. Right.
there's
more nuance to it than just definition of terms.
Yeah.
Yep.
Alrighty.
So people try to worship Yahweh with idols.
Bad idea for the record.
I'm again it.
So, obviously the Locust classicus of this, right, is the Golden calf.
Right, and I know we've talked about it at least a little on the show before that, right,
if we had a photo of it or if we had the thing, which of course we don't because it got
belted down, it would probably look like an Apeis bull from Egypt, seeing as folks had
just come from Egypt and an odd preponderance of Levites have Egyptian names.
So they were probably connected to Egyptian religion in some way.
before the Exodus. So I was likely would have looked like an
Apeisable but it wasn't purely an Egyptian phenomenon because of course the
Apeisable and everything else, this draws on the whole bowl of heaven, the
Haymot, the Hymeth traditions that we've talked about on the show several times
before. So this is kind of an assimilation of Egyptian and Canaanite idolatry and
even earlier.
forms of idolatry. But after Aaron makes the calf, what does he say? He says, this is Yahweh,
your God who brought you out of Egypt. Yeah. So this isn't him introducing some additional
foreign God. This is him using idolatry directed toward the true God. And you can see here, of course,
That's what is happening.
The God who...
created the universe, right?
We've now reduced him to this bull,
to being part of this tradition of male fertility,
virility, right power.
But that's a reduction.
Yeah.
Right?
Of the God who created the universe.
Brought him down to this place.
He's not up on the mountain with Moses.
We've now brought him down here where we are.
Right?
And now that he's here,
Now we can engage in ritual activity to get.
him to do what we want rather than he up there on the mountain telling us through Moses
what he wants us to do.
So this is an attempt to, again, invert in this pagan way, the way the true God operates
to limit him and gain control of him.
interesting you can see sort of this inversion this user
idea, if you think about the fact that when they're going to make this golden calf, the Israelites go and take off all their jewelry and all the gold they have to melt it down, well, where did they get that?
That's the gold that they pillaged from the Egyptians on the way out of Egypt.
So Yahweh their God had defeated the gods of Egypt as he said himself right on
Passover night. He had defeated the gods of Egypt including Pharaoh. He had
destroyed the army of
the greatest superpower in the world at the time in the Red Sea. He had done this and then
he had shared the spoils of that victory with his people. Right? And what did they do with them?
Yeah. They make an idol to try to get control of him. To try to limit him. Right? And so you can see
that element of inversion and use a
and then what do they do in terms of ritual activity with this?
That you, well, the most English translation say very politely that they sat down to eat and then they rose up to play.
Yeah.
As if it was like, hey, we had a nice meal.
Let's play freeze tag, right?
Not what it's saying, right?
This is, this is euphemism.
This is euphemism.
And this is describing what was very common in paganism,
which is orogistic worship.
And so we have the meal they're eating
is a sacrificial meal they offer sacrifices,
right, to the idol.
And then they feast themselves
and then enter into this.
frenzied state and
This included sexual immorality
Right as you would expect from orgyastic, but also went to a kind of general frenzy. There's often a company by violence
By a breakdown of social order
Right, and that was deliberate
And this is found all throughout pagan worship all over the place, right? This is like the purge, right?
this is not
And once again, modern reconstructed paganism, right?
Where they put on their like white gowns
and go and have their nice ritual in the woods
or they make something that they think looks like a Greek temple
and they go and have this nice, sing some songs
and pray some prayers that whatever pagan god,
whatever pagan god their worshiping will help.
them with their hurt feelings or something because someone was mean to them at target.
Whatever happened, right?
That's not what ancient paganism looked like.
Yeah.
Okay.
That's not remotely what ancient paganism looked like.
That's like a pagan, a very thin bogus pagan veneer splashed over liberal Christianity.
That's what that is.
Okay.
went so far, like you look.
at the the DNSE and mystery cults, they would enter into a frenzy where homophagy was common.
They would eat live animals. Yeah, like rats. Yeah, say not bugs or whatever people, but
mammals. Yes, like taking a bite out of them while they're alive, ripping them apart with their
hands of their teeth. And this friends eat state. Okay, we're talking about mass rapes.
We're talking about the purge.
Okay, this is...
And this was seen as a state of ecstasy, of divine ecstasy.
That's being entered into.
That's what the Israelites do while Moses is up on the mountain.
Okay, they didn't venerate a cow statue too hard.
This is a total other thing.
They're not remotely similar.
And there is not just a coincidental relationship between the transgressive nature of what was being done, and the spiritual experience they were having.
Right, they believed that the spiritual experience they were having was the product of
and intimately related with the fact that they were bursting all of these normal social bonds,
transgressing their marriages, transgressing social rules of morality.
Yeah, this is the idea of crossing the important.
Crossing this boundary into this quote unquote divine, well,
into a divine world, not divine as in God, but the gods.
Right, right, and...
And you see the same thing, by the way, when the Greeks and their Romans write about war.
Right, war in the ancient world was especially brutal.
Right, especially bronze, bronze age war was worse than iron age war because bronze doesn't hold an edge very well.
To basically have people clubbing each other to death with massive pointy mental clubs and mass.
Right.
blood brutality, right, but the glory of war for the Greeks and the Romans was this frenzied
experience, this frenzied ecstatic experience that the survivors had gone through. That's
what they exalted in in glorified because the place of war was another one of these places
where all of those rules, all of those structures, the no-most of the people, was stripped away
and was gone.
And so Homer can have the muses and the gods singing about the glory of the butchery that's
happening in war.
This is very foreign territory for us who have been in a Christian society for many centuries.
But this is where the pagans were.
And this is the territory that Israel entered into with the Golden Cat.
This is why it is so horrific.
And Moses reacts the way he does.
Right. This is like the not not just, oh, they fell back into Egyptian religion.
Like this is the worst of it. Right.
This is like all the worst that parts of paganism at the time.
They went rushing toward.
But this
link
fingering, you know, sort of approach to the true God, but from a pagan perspective,
again, is ongoing throughout the Old Testament.
Jeff Tha is another good example.
When people think of Jeff Tha, they think about the sacrifice of his daughter primarily,
but there's a story before that where Jeff Tha is a leader in war.
This is the place where he properly serves as a judge.
Israel.
And when you look at how he negotiates with Moab,
if you read what he says, he says,
well, Yahweh brought us here to Arland.
Kimosh brought you there to yours, Moabites.
Can't we all just get along?
Right.
There's a massive problem there.
Right, especially since if you read Dude on Army Chapter 2,
it explicitly says Yahweh brought the Moabites there.
But, right, he's probably well just...
and say, like, yeah, you guys got your God, we got ours.
Right.
You know, right?
And so yes, technically,
Jeff is worshiping the correct God,
but he's seeing him in very pagan terms.
Right?
And that's only emphasized by the whole human sacrifice thing.
Because the way this story is told,
at least the way it was told to be as a kid,
when we got old enough that we actually got
the story of Jeff that in Sunday school,
was, oh, like Jeff that came home
he thought like a dog.
a cow or a sheep was going to run out to greet him. What? Yeah, no. He was going to sacrifice
a dog. Yeah. I mean, dogs are especially in the Middle East. Unqueased. Yeah, are the grossest,
nastiest things that you could possibly. UncLEAT ANIMALS. Or a sheep or a cow was going to run
out to greet him. Have any of you ever better out sheep or cows?
When he says the first one to run out and greet me, he's planning on it being a human.
He just thinks it's going to be a slave or something.
Yeah.
Instead, it's his daughter.
Any sacrifices are, he does a human sacrifice to the God of Israel.
And I'm sorry, but if you're going to come to me and say, oh, he didn't sacrifice her.
just went in
became a consecrated version of the temple. I'm going to say this is the book of judges,
bro, there is no temple. Yeah, really smart people say that. So like you got to think
about context, there is no temple. The pagan shrine, there weren't virgins there,
eight to tell you. So, right, it's very clear what happens here. And if you read both early
Jewish sources and early Christian sources talking about Jeff the they don't
a lot of good stuff about Jeff that they say good things about Jeff this daughter.
They say Jeff this daughter is an image of Christ because she
goes silently to her death. Yeah, it's kind of a martyrdom,
right? So they compare her to Isaac in the Jewish cases and then through that comparison in
Christian sources to Christ. But yeah, so there's, Jeff there's a problem. But Jeff there's
another example that there's still a lot of Israelites who are looking this way.
And
At the end of that story, we get,
this is, again, part of the story,
if you actually read it,
folks actually read it.
There's somebody out there right now getting mad at me
and saying, I think Jeff is the same for some reason.
Read the Bible.
So at the end of that, you get this new feast that shows up.
Oh, they celebrated this feast thereafter.
That's not a feast, that's it.
anywhere in the Torah. That's how what the feast God gave the people. Yeah. Right?
They celebrate this feast. And the feast they're talking about is actually one of the
feasts that was celebrated in the northern kingdom of Israel after it split away that
didn't have the temple.
Right?
And that feast is this feast where they go looking for Jeff.
this daughter, this is an archetypal pagan festival practice, ritual practice. Yeah, probably
the most familiar one, which I'm pretty sure we've mentioned before on the show is the search for
Persephone that Greek pagans would do. Was that in Athens? Maybe elsewhere too. Where were the
the rights of Demeter. I don't think it was happened.
Because she gets speared it away.
on the intended by Hades and so the idea is, you know, we have to go looking for her.
Right. But there are examples of this all over the place. Yeah. Yeah.
And it makes you paganism, right? It's just Persephone is the one most people have heard of.
And so this is this whole episode with Jeff that causes the real cute of Israel to come up with
their own version of the pagan feast. And so that's a good segue moving to the Northern Kingdom.
when Israel is split.
to the Northern Kingdom of Israel and the Southern Kingdom of Judah.
First king of the Northern Kingdom is Jeroboam the son of Nebat, and God sends a profit
to Jeroboam, son of Nebat.
He says, if you keep all of my commandments and are righteous before me as David was,
then I will also give you a dynasty that will have no end.
Right?
We would dress before on the show.
Wait, what?
David kept all the command.
but we did that on another show.
I'll talk about Repents.
Of course, Jeroboam does not do likewise,
and so his dynasty lasts for two generations,
counting him himself.
His son becomes king and then assassination, it's over.
But Jeroboam, when he becomes king of the northern tribes,
has this issue,
Right of...
you know, David's son or David's grandson, Rihobom, is the king down there in Judah
and they have the temple in Jerusalem.
And that's where all the worship is supposed to be going on.
And a lot of the feasts of the Torah, right, say the day of atonement, obviously centered around
the temple sanctuary.
Right? So he doesn't want his people having to travel to this other kingdom to worship, etc. etc.
So he famously constructs the golden calves because the first one went so well.
But the golden calves at Bethel and Dan, Dan being at the extreme north, Bethel at the south of the northern kingdom of Israel.
And that way, no matter where you live in his kingdom, there is one of his...
gold and calf shrines that is closer to you than the temple in Jerusalem is.
So you can go there instead. And so we can see there that setting up these calves there has this
deliberate goal of localization. Yeah. Yep. Right. He is very much trying to localize
the God of Israel. And he's doing a thing that they're not doing down at the temple, which
which the temple does not have some statue of God that they are.
putting sacrifices in front of and you know, like, they're, you know. Right. So, but well, we don't
always think through about this is that the Northern Kingdom then based on these two shrines with
the Golden Caps, Jeroboam constructs an entire new religious system that goes with this.
Right? So he has his own priesthood of Levites. Right? There's a high priest in Jerusalem at the temple,
but he has his own priestly hierarchy of Levites. They're in the northern kingdom who are performing the ritual surrounding the golden calves.
He has his own feasts, like the one we were just talking about with Jeff, the different cycle of feasts.
This is a whole different set of ritual observances.
Right, that are borrowed, that are not sort of like.
the Samaritans did where the Samaritans later took the Torah and tweaked things, right?
So we could do them in Mount Gharism and so we could, right?
This is not a tweak of the Torah.
This is a tweak of the paganism of the surrounding nations.
Right?
This is patterned after their kind of worship.
And that being the official religion of the Northern Kingdom, that then opens up.
the possibility, which we'll talk about in a few minutes here, that Omri will later
actualize in the Omri dynasty in the Northern Kingdom to then begin to assimilate and
synchronize the Northern Kingdom's pagan religion, directed toward Yahweh and the various pagan
religions of neighboring nations.
And cutting other gods before me thing.
Yes.
Yes, which brings us to the having other gods before me thing.
So if the golden calf is sort of the archetypal example
from the Torah of trying to use idolatry
directed toward the God of Israel,
then the Locus Classicus for the second category
of parallel pagan worship, we might say,
in numbers at Baal Paor, right?
The Bale of Peor, which is a localization of Baal,
Baal Paor is a classic example also of a high place.
So you'll see throughout the Old Testament,
the Hebrew Bible references to high places.
You'll talk about good kings tearing down the high places,
and Bad King's building back up the...
high places, right? And these high places are a type of pagan shrine that is less than
a fully constructed temple, but a little more than the grove. It's in between category, where
you have an area that's delineated by a fence or a wall surrounding various natural features,
And it's a place, it's sort of a zone there then on a hill and it's high place.
ritual worship of various gods takes place. And so in this example of Alpo
or being one of them, there is this mixture which hopefully if not before people
will kind of be ready for now, given what we've already talked about in this
half of these foreign pagan women, drawing the men of Israel astray.
and references to the pagan worship of Bale, right?
And that's because these are the same things.
This is the same kind of orgyastic worship
from the golden calf.
It's just now being done with these quote unquote
priestesses or temple prostitutes,
as there are sometimes called,
who are there to facilitate that kind of worship
because Bale, Storm God,
This is a...
fertility, right? Shrine. And so the this orgy acid worst begins to take place. And
this escalates in the story to the point where a man takes one of these women into the camp
to continue these activities, walks past Moses and Aaron and the others, right? So not
Not only are they going out of the Israelite camp, which is...
to be kept holy, right? Going out of it and performing these acts of idolatry and sexual
immorality, but now this escalates with this man, now bringing that into the camp, into
the presence of God. And that's why Phineas has to go and make a shishka-bob.
And...
is not expecting that to. And put it in. Put an end to this worship, right? And so then this is
related to there's this plague, right, that breaks out. And the plague, when we really understand
what's going on in the story, the plague is not like, oh, they're doing bad stuff. God sending a plague
to kill them because he's mad, right?
or to punish them, right? Because the plague gets stopped, right? Not by just some active
repentance or it doesn't get stopped by the end of them fornicating and participating in
an idolatrous worship. It's stopped by a line of priests with incense, a censor failings.
Yes, like standing off right and standing between the living of the dead
right and and sort of blocking the progress of the plague. And so the plague, what the plague
is here is the plague is giving a sort of reality, giving a manifestation
to the spiritual destruction that Israel has brought upon itself
through engaging in this, idolatry.
It's giving that a sort of...
more tangible form so they can see it so they can understand it. Right? And that's why the answer to
this kind of corrupt pagan worship is the true worship of Yahweh the God of Israel. Right? That's
That's what stops it, right?
Because idolatry is a plague.
Hmm, right.
So.
just like in the previous category we could see that this kind of thing continues into the period of the judges.
So when we get to Gideon, right, Gideon's father apparently has a whole ton of idols because God has to come and tell Gideon to go reccom.
Yeah.
And then Gideon serves as purpose as the judge of Israel.
He is.
Gideon is a saint in the Orthodox Church.
He is on the calendar.
Yes, he's on the calendar.
Yesterday was his feast day.
Yes, he is listed in the Sinekzarian on that day.
You know, he's a little bit of a shifty character
because being a little bit of a shifty character
does not stop you from becoming a state.
Look at you, Jacob.
But part of his shiftyness at the end of his life,
which is what my favorite funny scenes in the Bible is,
he has all these people coming to him and saying,
You're trying
to make yourself king. You're trying to set yourself up as the king of Israel. And he's like,
what? Me? No. Never. Why would I do that? And then it says the text that his son, Avi
Melek was standing there. Avi Melek means my father is king. So he names his kid that. And
it is like, what? I would never make myself. See a little shifty.
But he has at the end of the story he has this e-fod and we're told
after his death, that Ephod becomes a snare for Israel.
It becomes an idol.
Right?
And this shows us that among a lot of the Israelites,
right, they were looking at things in a very pagan way.
Who is Gideon for them?
Gideon for their tribe is this founder figure.
Yeah. Right?
And so they kind of divinize him.
And uses ephod as an idol.
So that shows, again, this kind of idolatrous mindset is still around among a lot of the people.
Get excited folks, I'm about to talk about Samson, but only briefly.
As we keep going in judges, right?
Not going to talk extensively about Samson, but notice that when the angel comes to announce the birth of Samson,
We're told that his family lives near Beth Shemesh
Hey Shemesh literally means the temple of Shemesh the Sun God. So apparently Dan
It's cool with there being a temple to the pagan Sun God Shemesh
There doesn't have a problem with it and if you say well that probably didn't include Samson's family
I would point out that they named him after Shemesh. That's where the name Samson comes from
So again, you see this kind of
in syncretism going on. It's not that they don't acknowledge and worship Yahweh, it's just
they've got these other Godpagan gods too. And then in the last part with the Israelite
Civil War and everything at the end of Judges that we don't read as much because it gets
really gory and messed up. We read about a Levi who gets hired to come and serve an idol
in Dan. So this is the kind of thing that's happening.
Not hidden by the Bible. The Bible is how we know about it. It tells us about it.
Now, lest you think from what we said about Jeroboam, son of Nebatt and the Northern Kingdom,
that the Southern Kingdom was doing it right, we know that from the story of Solomon.
He married. Also a saint.
Also a saint. Yes, Solomon is a saint. He's on the calendar.
He's on the calendar in the Sinekzarian and Solomon.
Right? We even have the book of Ecclesiastes. We have his repentance at the end of his life for the bad stuff
He did that the Bible records, right?
but
Let me tell you when the church says somebody is a saint and the Bible says he does did bad stuff that doesn't mean he didn't do bad stuff
Right doesn't mean the Bible's wrong. He did do bad stuff
But people could do bad stuff during their lives and still become saints
Which is good news? Yeah, or should kind of how this thing works?
works. Yes.
And so, right, he takes on a whole lot of wives and concubines, right?
And don't be mistaken, concubines mean sex life, right?
Concubines is a much prettier sounding word.
It's like he had, you know, a bunch of girlfriends.
These, no, these are sex lives.
And a lot of them were foreign wives who he married to make alliances with foreign countries,
which he also wasn't supposed to be doing.
and we're told
by the Bible that he built shrines to the gods of those wives in a round Jerusalem.
This is part of why the kingdom gets divided. Why his son doesn't inherit all of Israel.
Why Jeroboam got to do the horrible things he did.
than that, we know from later on when his descendant King Josiah destroys them.
that he had set up a chariot of the Sun and idol
with horses in the temple courts Solomon had
Shemish Shrine
Shrine say that five times right with Shemish having been the pagan God worshiped in Jerusalem before his father David took it
Solomon built it
It was there until the reign of King Josiah so
So well, and we also know from what we...
which Asaya, that the later kings of Judah put more shrines in the temple courts to pagan gods.
So keep this in mind, the first temple from the time Solomon built it, to the time of its destruction
by the Babylonians minus this little window where King Asaya tried to clean things up.
Right? Was full of idolatrous shrines, according to the Bible?
Right? There was no sort of pure golden age period here.
with the first temple. Right? The worst thing about the second temple is that
Herod built most of it. Right? That's actually a little better, by the way, than the
first temple being full of idols. And so of course, Josiah, right, tried to clean
things up and destroy them, but we hear about his successors rebuilding the
high places. This is a big part of how Judah ends up in exile in battle.
on. Right? It wasn't for doing things right and worshiping impurity. Right? That's not how you end up in exile.
And further, we also know, because Josiah recently put an end to this as well, that
Molek worship was going on. Mostly in the Valley of Hennum, people want to argue about that now,
But hey, if you believe the Bible's true, I'm sure it was going.
on other places in the Northern and Southern kingdoms too.
But Molek worship was what we're talking about,
and this was very popular in certain Phoenician sectors,
was the sacrifice of your first born infant.
And this was as a burnt offering,
this was generally done with bronze statues
that were super heated.
Yeah, and this is
where you get this phrase in the Bible, passing your children through the fire.
Right.
To Molec.
And as God repeatedly points out, those aren't your kids, those are my kids
who I entrusted to you and you did this to them.
Right.
I won't go further into this, but there's a lot of political discourse in the
United States right now.
that revolves around parents, saying their children are theirs and they own them.
And I have to correct that.
Your children are gods.
They belong to him, not you.
And you have a responsibility for them.
Right? That should make it more dire, not less.
How how they're raised and what happens with them because you get to have to give an
account when you stay before the judgment seat of Christ.
for everything you said and did regarding them.
They're not sort of property for you to dispose of as you see fit.
They also don't belong to the state. I'll be even handed. They definitely don't belong to the state either. They belong to God.
And lots of states have gotten destroyed based on what they did to God's children.
Over the course of human history.
Um, that can happen.
again. Yeah, oh, it will happen again. But so, uh, there of course, that's right. The Southern
Kingdom, the Northern Kingdom in addition to the sort of paganized religion that Cherubos
Son of Nebatt starts. As I mentioned, when you get to the Omride dynasty, started by Omri,
his son Ahab, Omri marries his son Ahab to Jezebel. The bell in her name is Bale. If you didn't know,
who was...
daughter of the king of Sidon, one of the primary Phoenician cities, and so she came and brought
bail worship in alongside of it and seems to have maybe even wanted to displace
Jeroboam's religion with more of her family religion and a Hab seems to have been especially weak.
Bye.
But this is why it's this religious imposition.
It might say from a modern perspective, and the kind of idolatrous worship that we've been discussing that she brings into the Northern Kingdom that causes the entire Omride dynasty to get wiped out over the course of the end of first Kings beginning in second Kings.
Um
because they're the ones sort of deliberately responsible for it.
From the Bible, where I have seems like a more prominent figure than Omri, so some folks maybe
wonder why I keep calling it the Omride Dynasty. From the perspective of ancient history and the
ancient Near East and all the inscriptions we have from other countries, Omri is the most important
King of Israel, period, northern kingdom, southern kingdom, combined.
They referred to the Nordic Kingdom of Israel as the House of Omri for a long time until
its destruction.
We have inscriptions of this.
He gets six verses in the Bible that basically just say he was wicked.
He bought the hill where they built Samaria.
He died.
And as for the other stuff he did, read the official annals of the king who cares.
and then they move on.
to get to the story of Elijah, not even the story of Ahab his son, but the story of Elijah.
And so just a note here, because this is something obviously that comes up in scholarship,
this whole idea, you will see a lot of things in Old Testament scholarship,
referring to Israelite priests, Israelite priests do all kinds of things,
uh pre-exilic post-exilic
There's the pea source or so pea sources and the whole JEDP thing with the Torah, with
other the priestly source and other books of the Old Testament. Much is made of the Israelite
priests and how they were trying to enforce, you know, only the worship of the One God, only
from the temple in Jerusalem all along.
and they were the ones really enforcing this.
When you look at the actual picture,
Israelite priests becomes really problematic.
Because if you follow what we just went through
and you follow what the Old Testament Scriptures
Hebrew Bible says,
most of the priests, most of the Levites
who are serving priestly functions in Israel,
again, especially once it's divided,
but even with Solomon,
Even though the purity of the
Judges are pagans.
The vast majority of them.
Even the ones who are serving at the temple in Jerusalem,
a bunch of them must have been serving at those pagan shrines.
Right.
So, you know, you really have to,
to make that whole priest thing work,
you have to extend that priestly source.
have to make it very post-exil.
right? You have to hypothesize right and then you have to move the writing of
pretty much the whole Old Testament into a couple centuries post-exile to try
and make that work. Some people do. Some people try to do. Yeah. Some people try to
do. The Greek Old Testament tradition kind of abuts that because you start
having texts in the third century BC getting cr-
translated in Degree from that we know there were already multiple Hebrew traditions
of different forms of these books by the third century BC. Right, the exile ends at the
end of the sixth century BC. So I mean, we're not talking about a lot of time for all of
this stuff to get written and to have multiple streams of tradition diverge. So the whole
The whole thing gets pretty daisy.
That's all I'm saying.
Yeah.
And...
I don't think, oh, they were in Persia and they saw Zoroastrianism.
And that made them all monotheists makes a whole lot of sense.
I read about that on the internet, though.
I mean, they did become Zoroastrians.
They just said, Hey, we're going to make up a new kind of
religion that has never existed on Earth before based on seeing Zoroastrianism.
Okay, just like this one little piece of Zoro Astrian is
I'm sort of and we're going to rewrite all these tax we're going to rewrite the history
of our people based on this new religion that is somewhat inspired by zero asterism like
it's based on zero asterism the way like a Vincent Price movie named after an Edgar
Allen Poe story is based on Edgar Allen Poe.
Like.
All right, except at least those have the same name.
So with...
We're going to go ahead and take our second break.
And we'll be right back with the third half of Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
with help from Faith Tree Resources.
Have you ever felt distracted or disengaged in church,
but weren't quite sure what to do about it?
Divine Liturgy, the greatest invitation,
is the newest video course brought to you
from Faith Tree Resources,
and will help you better understand
and experience the peace God offers to us
in the Divine Liturgy.
This four-part series taught by some
of the church's most respected leaders
will equip you with resources and tools
to help you more deeply encounter the one true God.
Whether you're a parent, hungry to teach your children, a pastor looking to equip your
faithful or someone who wants to learn how to actively be present in the divine liturgy,
this course is for you.
Go to faithtree.org to get your copy today.
That's faithtree.org.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855.
237 2346. That's 855 AF radio.
Welcome back. It's the third and final. Well probably. Yeah, third and final half of the
Lord of Spirits podcast of this episode. Yeah. Of this episode. Yes. We did we did have that one
episode that had four halves. Yeah. That was it. But unless you have some secret plan that I'm not
aware of for half four tonight. I think that now I have to get up at 545 in the morning to help my
my kids kid.
the bus. So I'm motivated not to. They can't find the bus. Yes, that's right. Anyway,
your bus is occasional skills. Yes. The first, the first half we talked about pagan
idolatry, second half we talked about Israelite idolatry. And now we're going to talk about
Christian idolatry.
Yeah.
Well, it's also bad.
Yes, yes, we're not saying that because it's Christian, it's okay.
But yes.
Yeah, just putting Christian in front of something doesn't make it good unless we're talking about actor Christian bail.
She was excellent.
And the bail part is not bail.
Right, right.
It's more like hey um so uh
When we talk about, you know, it's a little tongue in cheek to call it Christian idolatry.
But what we're talking about is idolatry from a Christian perspective, which of course
is going to be Christian critiques and forbidding of idolatry.
Right?
plan it for a bit.
So and the perspective from which
Right, beyond what we've already talked about,
idolatry is critiqued within a Christian framework.
So, we have to start with sort of prohibitions of literal idolatry.
And what I mean by that is obviously Christianity, right, proper.
We're talking about the first century AD, the Apostles, right.
There is very literal pagan idolatry going on, right, all around them.
and
And especially when the apostles go out
into the Greek and Roman world and beyond it,
they are going to communities that are steeped in idolatry.
That's the whole self identification
of those communities, those cities, those people groups,
is based around idolatrous worship and festivals
and these things.
So within the pages of the New Testament
and in the early sense.
pre-constituting the Roman Empire, we find very literal prohibitions of the idolatry we described in the first half and really the second half, right?
So in fact not only was paganism still very much around in the Roman Empire in the first century, but it was sort of ascendant and had been deliberately revitalized
in the wake of
philosophical schools in the Greek and the Roman world. A lot of what anthropologists now would label traditional folk religion, which seems to be the origin of the word paganism, for example.
Yes.
Had kind of faded off.
There were still certain civic festivals that were still offerings, right, made to the gods,
but sort of active participation in these things.
The no-
number of sacrifices that were being made, especially government participation, right,
from the Senate, right, and these kind of things.
Sacrifices were still being done in this kind of thing, but they were done in this very
rudimentary way, right?
Sort of this is what we do, this is what we have to do.
There is even a certain amount, there are certain quotes you could find from Roman generals
and senators and this kind of thing.
and thinkers that sound pretty jaded as far as the gods go.
Right.
They, of course, were no atheists, but, right,
these were looked at in a certain way.
You find Greeks joking about,
referring to the sacrifices being offered
as the burning of the bones,
because as they pointed out,
like all the useful parts of the animal,
people were keeping for themselves,
and then they were just burning the parts
they didn't want, giving those to the gods.
He finds this attitude prevailing.
When Augustus becomes Augustus,
when Octavian becomes Augustus and becomes Caesar,
becomes the Emperor, he embarks on a massive project
to solidify the empire.
Right, you get the Eniad, right,
the new history of the Roman people.
You get Ovid in his Metamorphoses collecting
collecting a lot of the folk traditions.
religious traditions of the people throughout the empire.
You get, and you get Augustus himself really embracing his role as Pontifex Maximus.
We have at least one very significant intact statue of Augustus in which he is wearing the head covering of a Roman priest
to convey this role as Pontifex Maximus.
He begins to publicly
offer sacrifices and leave these festivals again. And this is tied to him wanting to re-embrace
the Roman tradition. So there's very much an emphasis on this coming top down on religious
observance, pagan religious observance from the empire during, for example, St. Paul's missionary
And that's part of what exacerbates the tensions that he faces.
incoming to some of these cities.
And is what is gonna later in future bouts of this traditionalism,
what's gonna bring about a lot of the persecution of Christians.
The persecution of Christians is sporadic through the later history of the Roman Empire until St. Constantine.
but usually when it erupts, it's during a push to re-imbe...
race, traditional religion, those pushes are often motivated by some calamity or other,
or problem or other within the empire, that they are returning to their gods to try to
solve. And of course, the Christians weren't going to join in with that, and so it became
a problem to be eradicated. But so when you read, especially St. Paul's letters to the Church
Corinth, right? Corinth is an ancient Greek city.
Now technically the one St. Paul writes to isn't that ancient because the Romans destroyed
it and rebuilt it.
But it has this legacy.
Come back, Corinth.
Yes, there's a reason they did that.
They did that because Corinth had been the head of the Corinthian League.
Corinth had been the city that gathered up the Greek city states when they were for
common defense and this kind of thing.
So when the Romans came to take Greece and wanted to make a statement, they made that statement
by leveling Corinth.
then rebuilding it to say don't get any ideas. But it has this legacy and is very much a part of
this idolatous revitalization. And so a lot of what St. Paul talks about, there's a reason St. Paul
keeps vacillating in those epistles between don't participate in idolatry and don't participate in
and sexual immorality, right, sometimes within a few verses, right, because...
as we've talked about in the first two hours,
these are deeply linked.
And there are these festivals in Corinth
where mysteries are celebrated
and we get this kind of orgyastic worship,
this breaking of social bounds and boundaries.
This is why in the epistles to Corinth,
St. Paul keeps talking about everything
being done decently in good order
within Christian worship.
about maintaining traditional hierarchies within Christian worship, because this is over against
a paganism that saw the transgressive breaking of these things as the means to spiritual ecstasy.
And he's trying to pull these former pagans now Corinthian Christians into being more former pagans
right to separating that and delineating what Christian worship is about.
from what pagan worship was about.
And you see the same thing with St. John.
There's this emphasis on idolatry in especially first John,
second and third are pretty short, but it's touched on a little bit.
But first John, you see this emphasis on idolatry because he's
writing to Christian communities and in around Ephesus.
Ephesus hub of idolatry,
place where there is the
Temple of Artemis, one of the seven wonders of the ancient world, the main source of the local economy.
And so he also, right, is that there has to be this delineation, right?
Because what St. Paul and John and the Apostles in general are doing is they're not only,
It's not only a question of no you need Christian worship to be like
our Jewish worship which is pure, not like that pagan worship which is evil. But there's
an introspective nature of it in terms of how St. Paul thinks about the history of Israel,
right, that they're aware of the failures of Israel as they're laid out in the Old Testament in
this regard. Yeah, so don't keep doing that guys. This was bad before. It's going to be bad again.
And so neither coming into the Christian context and trying to
worship in this transgressive sexual way.
Nor trying to have, trying to come and,
okay, well, I'll come and worship Jesus on this day,
and then I'll go worship Apollo on this other day,
and Artemis on this third day,
neither of those are acceptable options.
Neither the gods alongside the God of Israel,
nor the worship,
the true God in this pagan idolatrous way.
us away. Neither of those are acceptable.
Right?
Neither of those are acceptable.
And a bunch of former pagans coming into join Jewish Christians has the potentiality to go
in one of those two directions.
And especially in a place like Corinth where it seems that it was mainly former pagans and fewer Jewish Christians.
Right? That is that danger is there.
So in the
Roman Empire at least, paganism really ends in the four century and it doesn't end because
Constantinious successors go and murder all the pagans that's silly nonsense. It didn't happen.
St. John Chrysostom's mentor, his teacher of rhetoric, was one of the last generation of pagans.
lived a healthy life.
But the pagans of that era were very much no longer practicing the kind of things we've just been talking about.
Already Christianity had had an effect.
The, you know, to use very modern terms, right?
Both paganism and various philosophical schools that were in self,
were in self, uh, themselves as we talked about embedded in paganism still had to.
compete with Christianity in the marketplace of ideas, right? They had to, so as they saw
the world shifting around them toward Christianity, they had to take the Christian, many of them inherited
Jewish critiques of idolatry of their motive.
They had to take that seriously as these things start to shift.
Right. And so you get the formation of, for example,
neo-platinism in the late second and early third centuries,
which is just, hey, let's try to Christianize plate-nism.
Yeah, it's an attempt to make it more appealing to,
you know, like they're seeing, they can see where the wind is blowing.
Yes.
Yes, you know, and you get these
varying forms of nosticism that are basically like, hey, let's Jesus up our paganism a little bit.
I mean, wasn't it the case where we're Julian the apostate didn't he complain?
Like he complained that Christians would take care of even non-Christians and he's like, why can't
our pagans be more like this? Like he wants pagan staff Christian ethics.
Yeah. And that's why Julian the apostates attempts to kind of reinvigorate paganism ultimately
weren't didn't have a chance of working. Right. Because you couldn't go to even this more philosophically
minded last pagan generation and be like, no, we're going to start sacrificing, you know, we're
going to sacrifice 50 bowls to Jupiter. They're like, oh, well, okay. We're going to go practice the
Dionysian rights. They're like, not so much, right? They didn't find that as appealing by that point.
Right, and so all of that had really broken down. Right, and there was also
accompanying this, less we forget. Right, I mean, everything I just said, a materialist,
probably could have said, but there's also this other elements of the oracles not working anymore.
Right, that is Christianity spread and became illegal religion. A lot of the spiritual phenomena
upon which paganism was grounded. Seaced.
to the point that we have writers in that late pagan period hypothesizing, well,
Daemon, right, where we get the word Daemon, they must die.
They must get old and die because the ones who this oracle was channeling, they just
stopped.
Right.
Right?
So the spiritual experience, right, that the pagans were going off.
after they weren't getting anymore.
Because these demons, post Christ, post spread of Christianity,
aren't able to do it anymore.
These Christian lands.
And so paganism really dies on the vine
over the course of the 4th century in the Roman Empire.
And honestly, similar things happen wherever Christianity goes
and the nation's converts Christianity.
This happens in the rest of Europe, this happens in Russia, right?
Both pieces of it.
And paganism just withers and withers and dies, right?
So for most of us, right, for most of the people listening to this, there may be some literal
idolatry going on near you, there may be a Hindu temple near you or something where there's
literal, you know, sort of.
pay an idolatry going on probably not depending on what country you're in, probably not sort
of the orgyastic worship kind of thing, though there are still places where that kind of thing
goes on. But even if that's going on, it's probably not a big temptation to most of our listeners,
like, hey, I want to get me in on that, right? But, right, but there's another way that idolatry
out.
history has been talked about within Christianity. And that mode of thinking and
talking about idolatry and warning against idolatry is just as pertinent as it
ever was. And this isn't just sort of, okay, well all the pagans went away, so
the fifth century church fathers decided to come up with another allegorical
thing and call it idolatry so that
those commandments still had relevance, right? Because, of course, they saw, so we'll talk
about more next time, that they had no relevance to iconography. But this already starts
within the scriptures, within the New Testament. Idolatry is used in this way, specifically
by St. Paul. So St. Paul, their collotions and Ephesians, a lot of the contents parallel
each other.
I will not now go into all the weird theories as to why journal articles have to be written
dissertations have to be published.
Um, each the opportunity everybody.
Yeah.
Oh no, there's so much writing on this you don't want to go down that road.
You would have to read so much.
But Colossians 3, 5 and Ephesians 5, 5 are roughly parallel.
and St Paul uses idolatry in this other way.
Yeah.
Yeah, so in the Colossians 3.5 reference,
he writes,
put to death, therefore, what is earthly in you.
Sexual immorality, impurity, passion, evil desire,
and covetousness, which is idolatry.
And then in Ephesians 5.5, he says,
for you may be sure of this,
that everyone who is sexually immoral or impure
or who is covetous, that is an idolator
has no inheritance in the kingdom of K-
Christ and God. Right. So here's St. Paul identifies covetousness, right? Basically greed, yeah.
As idolatry, right? And it might be easy to say, oh, well, he's just analogizing. Right? This
is an allegorical thing that it's like idolatry. But pause for a second because notice in both of
of these places where he identified.
identifies it as idolatry, he connects it, he ties it to sexual immorality.
In the way that literal idolatry is tied to sexual immorality throughout the scriptures
as we've seen.
So what St. Paul sees here about covetousness and idolatry is, goes beyond an analogy.
seeing something in terms of how it works.
how covetous this works and how idolatry worked or works.
And so think about how we were saying in the first half idolatry works.
That idolatry gives you this handle or this grip on these spiritual forces that work in the world that are beyond your control.
That's the idea at least. Right. That's not what happens. That's the idea.
And think about how the love of money.
How man man.
Right.
And man man in air make is more than just money.
It's money property.
Your reputation and prestige.
A really good translation of it used to be substance back when in English you would say that someone wealthy and well respected was a person of substance.
person of substance.
But we don't say that as much anymore.
But it sort of entails all of that.
Right.
And when a person chases after that,
what are they doing? Why are they doing it?
Well, what St. Paul sees is,
they're using that to try to get a handle,
to try to get a grip.
Right.
On the forces that work in the world that they can't control.
Yeah.
You know, it's interesting.
interesting I've sometimes heard.
Idolitry used in this more metaphorical way as glossed as, you know, well, an idol is
anything that gets between you and God.
And I mean, I think that that's true on a certain level, right?
But I think it's also more than that.
You know, it's not that.
Then you're just saying all sins are idolitry.
Yeah, right.
Which people do that.
Yeah, but it's like, what's the point of having the category of idolitry?
if it's just...
and I'm frustrated. Yeah, I mean, so, um, yeah, I think this is, um, a really important point,
like that if you just spread that word out to me, to mean everything, then what does it actually
mean? Um, what's the point in using it? Um, and we actually have, so we have a caller,
we have Daniel calling from Virginia who, uh, seems to have a related, a related idea on his
mine. So Daniel, are you there?
Yes, can you hear me?
We can hear you.
Welcome to Lord Spirit's Podcast.
What is your question?
Yeah, this is my first time calling you guys.
I've found you guys in the process of Goat, the bounce from Jordan Peterson to Jonathan
Pagio and then Jonathan Pagio said you guys were killing it one night with a Twitter link
to the Giants episode and I've listened to everything.
kind of since then pouring. It's the Peterson Pazzo pipeline it continues. Yeah. I'll make
it relevant to my question too. Are we listening to, I was listening to Jordan Peterson's
biblical series. I grew up kind of non-denominational but I'm trying to sort everything through everything.
I was thinking you guys in the whole sphere.
And I was kind of glanced over at my computer.
I'm a software technology type person for profession.
I'm going to go over my computer while listening to him talk about
a dollar tree and things like that.
And also just through listening to the definition
that you guys are giving,
it started to concern me a little bit.
Just because we, there's a series of obviously,
There's a series of obviously, you know, bits and you know, switches that turn on and off.
There's a thing that we create.
You, in the kind of as Peugeot, will say,
you sacrifice your time and attention
as a software developer or even like an electrical engineer,
to kind of breathe life into the machine
to make it do what you want.
And I don't think of it that way.
I just think of it as a tool.
But I'm hoping that the father Stevens
can alleviate.
some of my concerns that we're just building one big mass of AI idle.
Did you just pluralize us as Father Stevens?
I don't know, so resist its futile. You will be.
I know it's been a long time since anybody did that, but yeah.
So it's okay, this is my life.
So what I would say is, I mean like...
There's not nothing to that.
Right.
You know, we talk about idolatry as tech knee,
this attempt by human beings to manipulate the world.
Right.
And as, so if you've listened ever since some
earlier episodes, you know that we've said
that technology in and of itself is not evil.
Right.
It's the, in many cases getting it too early
but the whole point being using it in a bad way,
that is the problem.
So, I mean, here we are.
Father Steven is in Louisiana.
I'm in Pennsylvania.
You're in the Holy Land of Virginia, where I happen to have been born.
And the only reason we're able to talk to each other live is because of computer technology.
So, obviously, we're not saying that that is an evil thing in and of itself.
But I do see...
think that if people are using it to control and destroy one another and to enrich themselves
at the expense of other people, especially beyond what they actually need, then yes,
it is in a way, it does become this handle of Maman, that it becomes this engine of human
destruction.
I mean, I haven't listened to any of Jordan Peterson's Exodus stuff, so I have no idea what he said about any of that.
But...
If it was more him spurring my...
It was more just the topic spurring my thoughts.
Yeah, I got you.
Yeah, I...
I don't know.
I mean, I still have thoughts about AI that are not fully formed.
I know Father Steven has some ideas about it as well.
But I
I'm not as alarmed, I think, as some people are.
I'll just put it that way, but that's just,
that's not a thought out theological position.
That's just the way that I am experiencing
how the world is actually functioning.
I don't know, Father, do you have something to add
or whatever on any of that?
Right, I mean, yeah.
I think what you said is true in terms of how it can be used,
right?
other.
I don't know where exactly to nail down what is the idle, like I don't think the physical
computer is the idle or the internet is the idle.
It may be that the idle in that kind of situation is sort of the curated version of oneself
that one creates online.
And I don't just mean making an avatar in meta or something.
I mean, everyone who uses social media as a phony.
That's the key.
carefully curate version of yourself that you put out there to the world.
That might be ultimately the idol because that's what you're using to try to kind of
take control of your own destiny and your own fate.
Because maybe you feel like you can't control those things about yourself in reality.
you enter and do a kind of...
realm of unreality where you can control those things.
What you look like, what you sound like, how you come off to other people.
So, yeah, in terms of the AI level, I mean,
I've seen the Apple on Star Trek, right? Like, I mean, you can envision, I've played
paranoia.
You can envision a world where there is an AI that becomes sort of an idol, right?
where people sort of serve it.
but Mrs. Davis recently.
But I don't think we're there yet in reality.
I think we're much farther from that in reality
than people realize.
I think like chat GPT for all of its amazingness
is really just Google and cross with an Eliza program.
All the old heads out there
and programming know what an Eliza program is.
Oh man.
That brings me back to me in the 80s.
To me, it feels like mad lives on steroids sometimes.
Yeah, yeah.
So I think we're pretty far away from that.
But I think there can be a way in which particularly
the way people now interface with the internet primarily
through social media can take on an idolatrous aspect.
But even that, the vast majority of people
in the United States are not on social media.
And if you talk about any given platform, it gets super tiny.
Yeah.
Um, so what that is still a danger when you get there.
So when building software, raid the Egyptians and deliver the good.
Or there you go.
Yeah.
Exactly.
Raid the Egyptians, but do not turn what you make into a golden calf.
Yeah, that would be bad.
That was so many of you guys have referenced the Simpsons.
the most best golden calf, funny golden calf moments ever.
I could have brought up a movie.
All right. Well, thank you. That's a good, that's a good question, Daniel. Thank you very much for calling in.
Thank you so much for taking my question. Yeah, you're welcome.
All righty. Ma'am and as the handle. Yeah. I mean, and I mean, like it's worth pointing out.
Because sometimes it's not, you know, you don't connect the dots, but let's connect the dots, right?
Certain things that always go together. The scripture always says that
idolatry and sexual immorality go together, right?
And you know, obviously in this terms of this orgyastic worship that you see in pagan ritual, but
what do we see in the people who spend most of their time
I'm trying to
get hold of Mammoth not just the wealth of fame. Yeah. Yeah. Like there is a lot of immorality
there and true or geistic worship. Yeah. It's the pursuit of altered states of consciousness.
Right. It's that same. It's the same thing. It's just not cast in specifically religious terms.
Right. Right. Yeah. We'll have Wall Street anybody. Yeah. They go hand in hand.
Right, they go hand in hand, they always will. And St. Paul saw that even when he's talking about
idolatry in terms of greed, um, that those go hand in hand. And so, um, to generalize a little more
out of that beyond just Baman, right? What we're talking about here is how can a concept become an
an item. Right? What does it mean to worship a concept? Right? And...
We have to realize that a concept is basically the same thing.
So a concept is something that is shaped, that is mentally shaped, and that then delimits something.
Right, it limits it, it rooses it, and then allows it to be manipulated.
Right.
So, for example, to use the example I use with Plato, right? Justice. Right?
When most people talk about justice today, they're not talking about like the divine energy of justice.
Right. God's activity in bringing about justice. They're not tying that to the God who created the universe who is infinite.
They have a concept of justice.
Here is what justice is.
Justice is...
fairness, justice is the redress of historical inequity. Justice is the punishment of the
guilty. But that concept, however it's defined, that definition is a delimitation, it is a
mental shaping and a mental reduction of the justice of God.
into this image, right, this, this delivered image. And then once it's been reduced to that
concept, that concept can now be manipulated. It's now an idea. You've talked about ideas,
how they can be instrumentalized, right. I can use that concept of justice to make an argument
to you, to make a presentation to you, and use it to manipulate you, and get you to do what I want,
Right by a P
healing to these concepts once I've defined them and
Delimited them and they allow me to get a handle on
These forces that are otherwise beyond my control
To bring about agreement to control other people who aren't necessarily going to do what I want and who might threaten me and my interest in various ways
so
I
Don't want to go all Calvin here
All right, who said that the
Human heart is a per-
perpetual factory of idols. But, and I'm talking about the mind. But a concept very easily
becomes an idol. The concept very easily becomes an idol when that concept has in our minds
at least any kind of divine agency attached to it.
Like justice, or love.
Yeah, yeah. You can always tell what people take.
People take one thing that is true of God, right, and then make it this overriding thing that eliminates anything else that traditionally is said about God and Scripture or whatever.
But they even delimited, right?
It's God's love. Here is what love is.
I'm not out of here just by definition.
And now I can weaponize that definition of love against you.
Right.
And all done a lot, any of these, right?
Any of these concepts to which divine agency can be attached, right?
And obviously that that applies to these concepts that are just related to God applies doubly
so to concepts of God, right?
Concepts of of God, right?
where we in our mind have an idea of God.
We have an idea of who he is, what he is like, what he does, what he doesn't do.
Yeah, and I think this is part of why so many of the church fathers are so insistent on saying,
even alongside the things that are traditionally said about God and our tradition,
sorry, that's still redundant, but even alongside those things to say,
we don't really know anything, you know, like we say these things because this is how God is.
We give them some...
but you cannot define God, you cannot put a line around him and say, well, this is who he is.
Right. Right. Because as soon as we start doing that,
we create an idol. We create a conceptual idol. And then, but that's attractive to us, because then we can use it.
Yeah. God doesn't do X. God will do Y.
Right. And we find this all over the place.
We find this all over the place.
Let me say, as we've critiqued many times on the show,
both in terms of Calvinism and in terms of universalism,
which, as we said, is deeply connected to Calvinism
because both are Plateness.
When you impose necessity on God,
that's a good warning flag that you've limited him,
that you're dealing with a concept.
You're dealing with your own personal Jesus,
not the actual Jesus who exists, right?
any time you try to limit the
fine God, you're doing that whether you realize it or not so that you can manipulate the concept.
Right. If I say this prayer, God has to save me. I'm worried. I'm scared. Okay, I said the prayer.
Now I'm saved. I don't have to worry. Yeah, I think it's it's really important to emphasize that
God is utterly free and idolatry is about making that not so.
Yes, yes. So maybe Calvin was right. He just needed a little more self-examination.
So that said, and because I couldn't resist the bit, what are some American idols?
Aside from Kelly Clarkson.
Right. God bless her.
Sir.
No.
I don't know.
What was with that two-tone hair back of the day, though?
That was just a weird thing.
I would not have thought you would pay attention
to the hair tone of Kelly Clarkson, but here we are.
She's from Texas, and I was living in East Texas
at the time, and it was kind of a thing there,
and I never had.
I didn't even, I don't even remember that it was a thing,
but it was kind of a thing.
I don't know who's the thing beyond Texas,
but it was kind of a thing, and that,
at any rate.
So, uh...
What are some things, right?
And again, you and I, Father Andrew, live in the United States.
So we have to speak from that, right?
I'm sure if you live in Australia or the Netherlands or Greece or England or wherever you may
be, Scotland Wales, don't really believe it.
Guam.
Technically the United States, but you go minions no.
Yeah, you're different.
Yeah, wherever you might be listening to this, there'll be shades of things right that might connect or you might just not like America's feel like what I'm about to say.
What are the things, the conceptual things other than wrong concepts, limiting concepts have got himself that have become idols first.
Where's the big one?
I think this is true in all of the
So he's a European descended nations, not just the United States, but probably also Canada,
also Western Europe, at least, Australia, etc.
Commonwealth countries.
And that is the state.
You see this unfold in real time in the 19th century in Europe.
there is the
Western European nations were secularizing sort of deliberately.
You see the iconography that we'll talk about more next time.
And imagery and even popular songs and these kind of things
that used to have religious associations be re-associated with the state,
with the leaders of the state, with the founder figures of
of the state in a way that isn't just over paganism, but is not a different phenomenon
either. Right. So the nation state itself becomes this idolatrous figure because the nation
state again is going to be this handle. It is going to give us a good life. It is going
to guarantee our safety and peace. It is going to get control of all these things that I'm
I'm scared of all these things that I-
worried about. I don't have to worry because the state, right? And all I have to do is my
sacred duty to the state to ensure that that all happens, right? This is idolatry. And then
politics becomes this sort of tech, right? Of how do we use the state to make those things happen?
Yeah, I mean, and you know, you mentioned all the the iconography of nationalism. I'm like,
like
God bless them.
I mean, you go to our nation's capital
and like you go to the Lincoln Memorial.
That is basically a pagan temple
in terms of its architecture, you know,
and you've got this.
Yeah.
Divided into the US Capitol with the,
it's called, the painting is called the Apotheosis.
Apotheosis.
Washington.
Yeah.
And mounting up into heaven to become a god.
Right?
I mean, yeah.
Yeah.
Now...
They meant it in maybe a different way at all being deists or whatever. I don't know but but like that's it's totally there
That's what that imagery is right is about
Right and and so you get this right but that idea of looking to the state
that idea of nationalism
Right where the nation state is our protector our savior. It's what we drive our identity from
Our community is not our
church, it's not the community of faith, we're not part of the nation of Christians, we are
this nation, that's what gives us our identity and our self-understanding, just a side note.
I know there are Orthodox folks out there on the internet who say things pro-Christian nationalism.
And some of you even evoke like St. Constantine to talk about Christian nationalism as if the Roman
when Empire was a nation.
state, like huge category mistake, the nation state is a different concept. But at least in
the United States, I think it bears thinking about that if the United States were to go the
route of Christian nationalism, where the laws of the country were based on Christianity,
The Christians who would be doing that don't think that I'm a Christian.
I mean, you wouldn't people fantasize about these things.
They figure that they're get to be in charge.
Their group is the one that's going to be in charge.
But that's not the case if you're an Orthodox Christian in the United States
where a tiny minority.
So, you know, you swass of our faith might get banned and made illegal as
necromancy. They might come and burn all our icons.
And if you think I'd be ridiculous, okay, then you don't know US history.
You don't know about or Canadian history.
You don't know about the anti-Greek riots in Toronto.
You don't know about a
the anti-Catholic violence that Protestants have carried out in the history of this country.
You don't know about the first US governor of Alaska
using residential schools to try to force Indigenous children to convert from Orthodox Christianity
to Lutheranism. So yeah, that's what Christian nationalism will get you guys. So leave off with that.
You don't want it.
Okay.
Anyway, back to our topic. The nation's it becomes this idol, right, becomes what is
looked to. Basically, it's got for these things to which we should be looking to God, right,
as the one who is actually, right. But again, we don't feel like we can get the true God
who created the universe, right. We don't feel like we can get him to do what we want him
do because we can't. Right? And we prefer something else like the state that we see may have the
power to do some of those things for us, and which we can get a grip on and a handle on at least
a little more readily. Yeah. Because it gets results. Right. Just like the pagans moved on to the demons
because they couldn't get the true God to do what they wanted.
Another big one.
For us, our culture is war.
Right?
Not war in the sense the Romans did.
Although a lot of horrible things happen in war.
If you don't understand that, go and actually, instead of just talking about how great veterans
are, everyone listening to this should go actually meet some and talk to them.
A lot of them, if you could use someone to talk to.
In combat.
Yeah.
And find out about their experiences.
Right.
Um...
But so it's not in that sense where you know while horrible things happen, it's not about going and exulting in bloodshed and, and, right, horror, right.
But there is this idea that somehow war brings out virtue in people.
But there is this weird idea that by the state being perpetually at war and by war and threat
of war.
the world again. Okay, now we don't have to worry. Right? Now we're the rest of us who aren't over there. Right?
We're going to go fight them over there so we don't have to fight them here. Make people world safe for democracy. Right. Like, okay, now, now we're safe because that's going on.
And then you get really over the top stuff. Like I'm sorry, the battle him and the Republic. Right? As Christ died to make man holy, let us die to make man free.
Yeah, that's the original lyrics by the way everybody.
The, let us live to make men free is an edited version.
Yes.
I'm sorry.
Comparing the death of union soldiers to the death of Christ.
Right.
Like it's hard to argue.
That something idolatrous hasn't happened here.
That something isn't being put in God's place that isn't God.
Yeah.
And obviously in our culture, sexuality.
Yeah, I mean, especially in the way that everything is expected in certain contexts, everything
is expected to make way for certain concepts of sexual identity.
Right.
And it's moved from action to identity.
Yeah.
.
Right? The sense of self. Again, not derived from God, but being part of a quote unquote
community, not that there's any actual interaction in community and mutual support most of the
time. But just we all identify the same way. Therefore we're a community. Yeah. And I mean,
you know, we've talked about this before in the show as to why this is becoming more possible.
And it's because it's because of the stuff that Daniel said, you know, that people are
pouring their lives into machines.
And the 3D world that includes our bodies is less and less on our minds.
Right. Right. And in the United States at least, and I don't know how much this is a product of US culture
and how much this is widespread. So folks outside the US would have to tell me,
although I don't know that I want to know much more detail on this.
But the United States at least, uh...
sexualized material. I mean, we're talking about pornography, right? The entire sex industry in the United States has become over the last couple of decades increasingly violent.
Yeah. Because it just needs to be more extreme because that's how idolatry works and how addiction works.
It's not about, it's not about like love or sex is an expression between two people.
It's choking people, spitting on people,
demeaning people in other ways, right?
It's literal violence.
Right? It's more and more transgressive. Yeah.
Because remember what we said, as OJ asked to, the transgression is what produces the experience.
Right? The lawlessness is what produces the experience.
The quasi-religious experience.
Right? And then of course, right? We come back to Maman.
Right where we have this
fascinating, at least again in the United States, we have this fascinating God named
the economy. We must all make sacrifices for the economy. We must all do our bit for the economy.
The economy is good. The economy is bad. We must appease the economy.
But again, if I could just get some more money, if I could just get some more fame, then
then I'll be in control of my destiny.
Then I won't have to worry.
Then everything, I'll be safe.
then they will all come together.
That's just idolatry.
Yeah.
Yep.
So flee for miles.
As the Apostle says.
You know, I've been, I've been, I've been rolling around in my mind the question of
what I might say at the end here.
But and the thing that finally came to me is I think that
Some people actually, I don't think this, I know that some people actually use the church itself as a kind of idol.
And I know that some people would recoil from that idea, right?
I've even heard people say or seen them say on the inner webs, things like, well, can Christ be separated from his church?
In other words, you know, it's not possible to treat the church as an idol because Christ is a kind of idol.
the church. The church is Christ, right? And sometimes they'll say that in the context of
apologetics against other Christian groups, essentially saying it's impossible to follow Christ
unless you are Orthodox effectively. And that question aside, which is a whole big interesting
discussion but this issue of treating the Church as an idol.
So...
So if Christ and the church are simply the exact same thing and completely coterminous in every possible way, then why do we bother having two words?
Why do we talk about Christ and the body of Christ?
It's not because they're separable, but even that aside, I'll just grant that.
that there's
even if one wants to make a total identification between Christ and the Church, which I don't think is correct.
It is still possible to treat the Church as an idol because what happens is people have a concept of the Church that they are worshiping,
a concept of the Church that they are using as you said, Father, as a kind of handle on the world.
Right? What does that look like? Well, it looks like a lot of different things.
One way that it can look is when people
have an idea of a particular time and or place in church history and make that the end all be all of what it means to be Christian.
You know, you can usually note that they're doing this because they'll have the word holy and then the name of some time place empire kingdom or whatever after that word.
You know, in holy blah blah, it was this way and we have to get back to that.
that.
So there's this kind of
toxic nostalgia that sometimes exists
sometimes people will idolize
elements of church life
Probably the most common is monasticism
And the weird part about it is this is often being done by non-monastics
You know and the very otherness of it I think is part of what enables people to turn it into an idol and so they'll say well
These men...
fathers say this and that's used as a manipulation over and against. In many cases, the rest of the tradition of the church, you know, the rest has to submit to that.
People can idolize the liturgical life of the church. They can worship worship.
You know, and you can note that that's happening because then the way that it gets used like I have witnessed and been told
of stories of clergy serving services who are acting in abusive ways because the people
around them are not doing exactly the thing they're supposed to do.
And I don't just mean like offering proper correction and whatever, but like yelling and
even I've heard of people throwing things right, that kind of thing.
The authority within the church can be treated in an idolatrous manner.
is the key.
that right now in some parts of the world, if you are an Orthodox clergyman, and you preach
something that you know is true, but is not popular with the government and church leadership of
your time and place, that you can be penalized and even arrested, find, I mean, this is turning
church authority into an idol, right? I mean, I could go on and on. I could go on and on and
But how do you know you've turned some element of the church or your concept of the church into an idol?
It's when it takes people away from Christ himself.
It's when it takes people away from the life of following the commandments of Christ.
Right. It's when it's used as a weapon against other people, manipulation against other people.
And for one's personal self-aggrandizement, which could be, you know, about money and power and all that.
and power and all that.
that stuff, but it could also be about owning your opponents, right? People can turn theology
into an idol. It just becomes a bunch of words that ultimately don't point towards some life
in Christ, but are about defeating other people and winning arguments and so forth.
There is a lot of this within the Orthodox Church of our time on display. It is happening,
and it is very sad.
I'm not saying it's predominant necessarily. I don't know enough about what everybody is doing to be able to say that, but it is definitely out there and there are people who are
being driven away from the church, whether because they never join it or because they've just had enough because people are treating the church as an idol and not as the body of Christ.
Right?
So how do we guard against that?
How do we flee from that idol?
Well, number one, we should remember that our concepts of the church are not the church.
The church is the living body of Christ.
It is we who are in it.
It's not an ideology.
an actual community and it is in the world to do
the works of Christ in the world. That's how we are his body. We are his powers and his nexus of
powers and we are potential in the world. That is who the body of Christ is. And so where you see
people being made saints, made to live the way that Christ lived and to be the way that Christ is,
is, then it's being done right. But when you see
it used to destroy other people in whatever way, then it's become a
Dollar Tree. Then it's about control, right? So,
flee from idols, love Christ above all. And, um, you know,
remember that following the commandments is the foundation for
all of the rest of Orthodox tradition. And if you're not living in
such a way that you're following the commandments.
And according to the Scriptures, you do not love God.
And if you don't love God, then you're not really a Christian, not really.
And all the rest is just an idol, ultimately.
So that's what I would have to say here at the end.
So in past episodes, I've come out against Pasta, the nuclear family.
And most recently empathy.
So tonight I'm going to come out against delayed gratification.
This is something we've been taught.
Christ tells a parable about delayed gratification.
It's often labeled in our English Bibles as the parable of the rich fool.
this man who's very
prosperous. He fills up his barn. He builds more barns. He fills those barns.
Finally, he has all of this grain and all this wealth stored up. He says, Ah, good.
Now I'm set. I can take my leisure. I can relax. And God comes to him and says,
You fool. You're going to die tonight. And in a lot of cases, we've had the
opposite ground into us.
where all of the actual living of life, all of the good things of this life, are always
after a then.
And there's always something before the then.
You have to attain a certain level of success.
You have to get a certain level of education.
You have to achieve certain things.
Then you can get married.
Then you can have kids.
Then you can relax.
Then you can enjoy life.
Then you can have friends and spend time with them.
Then you can have some kind of leisure time.
Well, you have to work so many years, but then, you know, someday you'll retire and then
you'll be able to enjoy your golden years.
You'll be able to relax.
You'll be able to spend time with your hypothetical grandchildren since you didn't get to spend
with your children because you are working all the time.
There's always this then.
And oftentimes what comes before the then is an idol.
It's an idol.
It's the thing you're using to get a grip on your life and get a grip on the world so
that then you can relax and do the things you should do or want to do.
There's this other thing I gotta do first because otherwise, it
won't be safe to do those other things.
I can't relax and do those other things.
I'll have to worry.
Gotta make sure everything's squared away first.
Even more tragically,
nowadays, for a lot of us,
there's not even a then.
There's just what's before it.
There's just, I'm gonna have to toil away at this
until I die.
It's just I'm gonna have to tread water.
I'm gonna have to endure this.
I'm gonna have to survive this.
First, as long as I can.
We've realized that those things about retirement or those things about having kids late
in life or those other things they don't actually work.
They don't actually end up happening.
so there's sort of nothing in front of us but toil.
worry and anxiety, that'll probably lurch into despair. But what all of those kind of
idolatrous calculations have in common is that they leave out God. They leave out his
existence. They leave out his activity in the world. Right? They leave out his involvement
in the room.
world. The way that he and his very self, right, is active in moving in the world and
in us. They leave out the fact that he knows what we need, that he is the one in control
of all these things, not us. No matter what handles we find, what levers we pull, it's
him. That he is the God who created the universe, that he doesn't...
do what we want because often the most disastrous thing God could do to us is to give us what
we want or think we want in a given moment.
And we worry and we put ourselves into this despair and toil and stress. We deny ourselves
the good gifts of God in this world and the good things of this world because we ignore
and we forget about him.
So because God is real, because of the love of God expressed in our Lord Jesus Christ
for us is real, we don't have to be afraid, we don't have to worry.
We can live now.
We can love and enjoy community now.
We can have families now.
We can have friends now.
We can enjoy his good gifts now.
It's not even that hard to do.
You actually don't need
maman to do most of these things.
You can get together with friends and cook food and eat it.
Doesn't have to be fancy food.
It could be ramen.
You can spend time with
with your kids, your wife, your husband, your girlfriend, your boyfriend, your pals, you
can go and talk to and interact with actual humans in person without curating who you
are and what you look like and how you come off.
You can touch grass like all of these things are available to us all the time.
If we stop for a second from all the worrying and all the anxiety.
And remember that God is real.
And that Christ is real.
And that even when we forget about Him, He doesn't forget about us.
So when the gratification we're talking about,
is the blessings of God,
is the worship of God, is the love of each other,
do not delay that gratification.
Do not delay it one second.
It's yours now, because if you delay it, you'll never get to it.
That's what I have to say.
Well, thank you, and that is our show for tonight.
Thank you, every word, for listening.
If you didn't get through to us live, we'd still like to hear from you.
You can email us at LordofSpirits.nv.com.
You can message us at our Facebook page, or you can leave us a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com.
Slash LordofSpirits.
and join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays.
days of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern, 4 p.m. Pacific. God money don't want everything. He wants it all.
If you're on Facebook, which as you've heard, you probably should not be. You can still follow
our page, join our discussion group. There is good there. I felt it. Leave reviews and
ratings everywhere, but most importantly, share this show with a friend who is going to benefit from it.
We'll finally be sure to go to www.inxfordfaith.com, stroke, support, and help make sure we,
and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
Bow down before the one you serve.
you're going to get what you deserve.
Thank you, good night, and may God bless you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits
with Orthodox Christian priests, father Andrew Stephen
Damick and father Stephen DeYoung,
a listener supported presentation of ancient-
faith radio. And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne
and the beasts and the elders and the number of them was ten thousand times ten thousand
than thousands of thousands, saying with a loud voice worthy is the land that was slain to receive
power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing. Revelation chapter 5
versus 11 through 12.
You